<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of marriage with a defence of the 32th article of religion of the Church of England : viz. bishops, priests and deacons are not commanded by God's law either to vow the state of single life, or to abstain from marriage : therefore it is lawful for them, as for all other men, to marry at their own discretion, as they shall judge the same to serve better to godliness.</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28670</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10736400</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10736400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45578</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45578)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1404:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of marriage with a defence of the 32th article of religion of the Church of England : viz. bishops, priests and deacons are not commanded by God's law either to vow the state of single life, or to abstain from marriage : therefore it is lawful for them, as for all other men, to marry at their own discretion, as they shall judge the same to serve better to godliness.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 103 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. and are to be sold by R. Chiswel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed : T.H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Celibacy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF MARRIAGE, WITH A Defence of the 32th Article of <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England; VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons are not commanded by God's Law, either to Vow the ſtate of ſingle life, or to abſtain from Marriage; therefore it is lawful for them, as for all other men, to marry at their own diſcretion, as they ſhall judge the ſame to ſerve better to godlineſs.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 13.6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marriage is honorable in all, and the bed unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed: But Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Tim. 3.2.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Biſhop then muſt be blameleſs, the husband of one wife.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Theophylact. on Tit. 1.6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Chiſwel,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful <hi>Robert Raworth</hi> Eſq.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Argument of this ſmall Treatiſe is ſo great, that I preſume I need not Apologize for it: 'Tis <hi>Marriage,</hi> the Ordinance and Inſtitution of God himſelf; that which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> holds a Sacrament, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with other Reformed Churches, a Myſtery. 'Tis that which our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> honoured, by being born, though of a Virgin, yet of one that was married to a Husband; by his preſence at, and by working his firſt Miracle, of turning water into Wine,
<pb facs="tcp:45578:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>at the Celebration of a Marriage at <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee.</hi> 'Tis that which the Holy, Ghoſt in the Scriptures honours, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring therein the joys of Heaven to a Marriage-Feaſt; and by making the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of <hi>Abraham,</hi> a married perſon, and the Father of the Faithful, the Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of all Saints in Heaven, whether they were married or ſingle on earth. 'Tis a ſubject, of which that great Scholar <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> hath written, namely, both <hi>de Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus,</hi> and <hi>de Inſtitutione Matrimonii;</hi> as has alſo <hi>Ludovicus Vives de Conjugii Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine &amp; utilitate.</hi> 'Tis that which the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Martyr Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> bleſſed God for, and in commendation of which that Saint of the Lord, (which one calls that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God) Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> who when he was in Priſon, and there being ſome hopes of his deliverance and freedom, being asked what he would do in caſe he ſhould be releaſed. Anſwered, he would marry; being, I queſtion not, of that holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Paphnutius</hi> his mind, who at the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> declar'd, <hi>That the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb facs="tcp:45578:3"/>of man and wife was a holy chaſtity.</hi> 'Tis the ſhame of this Generation, that ſo many men and women live in common, as if they underſtood that noted ſaying, <hi>All things are common amongst Friends,</hi> of a Community of Women and of Wives alſo, as of other goods. My wiſh therefore is, and it ſhall be my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the uncleanneſs and filthineſs of this age, may not be puniſhed with a Deluge of Popery; I mean, by God's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us over to Spiritual Adultery, or the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And now having mentioned that Church, give me leave to ſay, that ſhe is juſtly branded with the name of, <hi>The Mother of Fornications,</hi> and thoſe too Corporal as well as Spiritual. What other Church in the world allows of publick Stews and Brothel-houſes? where, but amongſt her Sons, was it pleaded in their excuſe, that they are as neceſſary as a Pump in a ſhip, and a Sink in a houſe, to keep all clean, And although they would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that their Church is pure and clean,
<pb facs="tcp:45578:4"/>yea, both Militant and Triumphant in their holy Societies of Monks and Nuns, that theſe are like the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> whiter than the ſnow: Yet if we may give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to their own Authors, ſuch as <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Virgil, Book</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>de Inventoribus rerum,</hi> ſpeaking of their Orders of Monks, he ſaith, <hi>That it were behoveful that thoſe dregs of men were cut off and burnt, and that with their filth they ſhould no longer defile God's ſervice.</hi> And <hi>N. de Clemangis,</hi> a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Paris,</hi> who in his Book <hi>de Corrupto ſtatu Eccleſiae, c.</hi> 21. ſaith of the Nuns; <hi>Shame forbiddeth me to ſpeak of them, leſt I ſhould mention a company of Virgins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to God, but ſtewed, deceitful, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Whores, with their Fornications and Inceſtuous works: For what, I pray, are Nunneries now adays, but the execrable Brothel-houſes of</hi> Venus, <hi>the Harbours of wanton young Women, where they ſatisfie their luſt? that now the vailing of a Nun, is all one, as if you proſtituted her openly to be a whore.</hi> So he. I ſay, if we may believe theſe and other their own
<pb facs="tcp:45578:4"/>Authors; our Church, who hath none of theſe Convents for ſingle perſons, and who allows of the married life of the Clergy, is more holy and honorable than <hi>Rome.</hi> And I doubt not, but our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, though married, multitudes of them will preſent themſelves, and their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, chaſte and pious Conſorts, with innumerable others of their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as chaſte Virgins to Chriſt. And whereas the Papiſts tell us, there are three ſpecial Crowns in Heaven, one for them that overcome the World, another for them that overcome the Fleſh, and a third for them that overcome the Devil: If ſo, I dare promiſe many of our Doctors, though married, to each of them three Crowns in Heaven, far beyond the Popes Triple Crown on Earth; namely, to our Learned and Laborious Doctors, who by their Writings overcome the Devil; to our married Doctors, who by their chaſte Wedlock overcome the Fleſh; to our couragious Doctors, who are ready, if God call them, to Martyrdom; to aſcend
<pb facs="tcp:45578:5"/>to Heaven, like <hi>Elijah,</hi> in a fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, and ſo overcome the world: I ſay, to theſe I dare promiſe three Crowns in Heaven, beſides a fourth to them and their Religious, Modeſt and Chaſte Conſorts, <hi>viz. The Crown of Righteouſneſs, which is laid up in Heaven for all them that love the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Although neither the ſubject I treat on in the following Diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Marriage, nor the Church of <hi>England</hi> her Doctrine in the 32 Article of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which I defend, allowing perſons in holy Orders to marry, need any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy; yet I humbly beg your pardon for any weakneſs or miſcarriage you may find in my manner of treating of theſe things. And I humbly preſent this ſmall Piece to you, coming into the World from, as it were, under your roof; and beg your excuſe at leaſt, if not your Approbation and Patronage of it. If any of our Romiſh Adverſaries ſhould quarrel the Doctrine of our Church on this occaſion, you have ſuch Learned
<pb facs="tcp:45578:5"/>Friends and Acquaintance, and thoſe who have opportunities, advantages, and courage ſufficient to defend their chaſte Mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and their own chaſte Wives, againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Goliah</hi> amongſt the Romiſh Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines.</p>
            <p>Sir, I humbly thank you for your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to me, and your care of the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our Society; and ſhall, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as my duty binds me, pray for you, and for your good, your pious &amp; charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſort, that God would crown you with all the bleſſings of this and the other World.</p>
            <p>Sir, I have one thing more to intreat of you both, which I am confident nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of you, being ſuch good friends to our Church and Clergy, will deny, that is, to joyn with me in my prayers for the Tribe of <hi>Levi, Let thy Urim and thy Thummim be with thy holy One, let the ſound of</hi> Aarons <hi>bells be ever heard, and the ſmell of his Pomegranates always per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume the Church of God, and let there be
<pb facs="tcp:45578:6"/>found at laſt, of the Tribe of</hi> Levi <hi>amongst us, as of other Tribes, twelve thouſand ſealed ones. And that there may never want a ſupply of able and good men for the work of the Miniſtry, Let the Rod of</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, <hi>I mean the Univerſities, ever flouriſh, and yearly bud, bloſſom and bring forth ripe Almonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very much obliged, and very humble Servant, <hi>T.H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 1. 1673.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>wo things I deſire to premiſe: Firſt, That I do not pretend in this ſmall popular Tract, to teach Men, Brethren and Fathers of the Church, them, and their Wives, Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micks: But yet ſhall beg leave to tranſcribe a paſſage out of</hi> Luthers Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquia Menſalia, <hi>which I deſire our Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Clergy would conſider,</hi> viz. That one cauſe of the unmarried lives of Prieſts (to wit, in the Papacy) was, that the faults of the Prieſts wives were offenſive, ſo that when the Prieſts ſhould reprove the wickedneſs of others, then the people would hit them in the teeth again, and ſay, why did not they reform their own wicked wives? <hi>And truly I could wiſh, that I might have cauſe to ſay of all the Married Clergy, and of all others in the ſtate of Matrimony, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, I am, I may ſay of many,</hi> Ye have no
<pb facs="tcp:45578:7"/>need that I write unto you of Conjugal love and duties; for ye your ſelves are taught of God to love one another. <hi>To this purpoſe it was we adviſed by a Right Reverend Father of our Church</hi> viz. <hi>the B. of</hi> W. <hi>to all ſuch as his Lordſhip mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, often to read over the Office of Marriage that ſo they might the better remember and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their duties each to other. And truly I could heartily wiſh and beg of the Right Reverend th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fathers of our Church, that if ever they ſhould reviſe our Liturgy, which even ſome good men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that the duties of Man and Wife, Parent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Children, Maſters and Servants, might b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appointed to be read on the Lords days (after the reading of the Commandments) out of the Epiſtle to the</hi> Epheſians, <hi>or</hi> Coloſſians, <hi>or both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond thing I deſire to premiſe is, that I do not preſent you with a Regular and Scholaſtical Diſcourſe, either of Marriage, or of the difference betwixt the Church of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Rome, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Marriage of Prieſts, or perſons in holy Orders; but offer, as to the latter, ſome Collections out of Dr.</hi> Field <hi>his Fifth Book of the Church Dr.</hi> Fulk <hi>and Mr. Cartwright their Annotations on the</hi> Rhemiſts Teſtament, <hi>on</hi> Matth. 8. <hi>and on the Epiſtles to</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Titus, <hi>Mr.</hi> Perkin'<hi>s his Demonſtration of the Problem, Dr.</hi> John <hi>and Dr.</hi> Francis White <hi>concerning this Argument, and others, together with ſome of my own obſervations. The truth which is on our Churches ſide, is chiefty
<pb facs="tcp:45578:7"/>maintained, and the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>confuted by the Authority of the holy Scriptures. Biſhop</hi> Hall <hi>in his Treatiſe of the Honour of the Married Clergy,</hi> page 124. <hi>obſerves, that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>teaches contradictory to the Holy Scripture:</hi> The Spirit of God <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> ſaith, that <hi>a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop may be the husband of one wife;</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſays, a Biſhop may not be the husband of any wife at all: The Spirit of God ſays, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is honorable amongst all men;</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſays, Marriage is diſhonorable to ſome: The Spirit of God ſays, <hi>to avoid fornication, let every man have his wife;</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> like a quick-huſwife, ſays, ſome Order of men ſhall not have a wife, though to avoid fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>So that as another Author notes, amongst them, Marriage only, and not Fornication, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the dignity of a Clergy-man; and that Fornication has been allowed to Prieſts and Fryers, in compenſation for their reſtraint from Marriage; three or four Whores, as part of their ſpiritual Preferment: And probably ſuch foul Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Practices, made</hi> Luther <hi>ſo zealous for Matrimony.</hi> I took a wife <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> therewith to upbraid the Devil, and to confound the whoring in Popedom; and in contempt of that naſty Letchery in Popedom, which is very great and abominable, <hi>Luth. Col. Menſ. The ſame Author tells us, that under Pope</hi> Julius, <hi>was exerciſed an abominable Letchery and Whoring in</hi> Rome. At
<pb facs="tcp:45578:8"/>the ſame time, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> was a Cardinal that had a married wife; the which being known, he was conſtrained to forſake her, but in leſs than a years ſpace he took her again: Now when the Cardinal dyed, his wife wept bitterly, and ſaid, <hi>ſhe had an honeſt husband, who contented himſelf with one woman:</hi> The Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> wondering to hear the ſame, cryed, <hi>O Sancta Maria!</hi> for, <hi>ſays Luther,</hi> Chaſtity in thoſe people is rare Veniſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as we have the holy Text on our ſide, ſo have we the Fifth Canon of the Apoſtles, the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of</hi> Paphnutius <hi>a holy Biſhop; and with him concurred the whole Council of</hi> Nice, <hi>the Sixth Council of</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>Can.</hi> 13. <hi>and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Greek Church to this day, ſo far as to juſtifie the lawfulneſs of Prieſts officiating about the holy things of their Function, notwithſtanding their being married.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And further, to juſtifie our Church and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of our Clergy, we have the Conceſſions of many of our Adverſaries, as</hi> Franciſcus a Sancta Clara <hi>obſerves, that the Celibacy of Prieſts is not</hi> de Jure divino, <hi>but by the Law of the Church; and that the Pope may diſpenſe therewith, and ſome ſay doth diſpenſe with the married Clergy in the Greek Church; and others in his name, 'tis ſaid, have made Overtures of the like favour to the Engliſh Clergy; and in caſe they would be his dutiful and obedient Sons, be would be an Indulgent Father to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly, It is worth the conſideration, on our behalf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this matter, that ſome of the beſt men of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>ſuch as</hi> Eſpencaeus, Aeneas, Sylvius, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydore Virgil, Eraſmus, <hi>and others, have deſired that the Law of forced Celibacy might be taken away, to prevent the great ſcandal that is given by the filthy lives of the Clergy. Foraſmuch then as the Engliſh Clergy have had the poſſeſſion of their wives for above a thouſand years after Chriſt; and again, have had them reſtored to them by Law at the Reformation, they have no reaſon to quit their ſo juſt and ancient Rights, and with one half of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and to be contented with Lemans, inſtead of Wives; and Nephews in room of Sons. I ſhall diſmiſs thee, Reader, when I ſhall have told thee, that the fig-leaves wherewith the Romaniſts ſeek to hide the nakedneſs of their Church in this cauſe, are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fily blown away by Dr.</hi> Field <hi>of the Church, Dr.</hi> Francis White <hi>his Defence of his Brother Dr.</hi> John White, <hi>by Biſhop</hi> Hall <hi>his Treatiſe of the honour of the Married Clergy, and by</hi> Calixtus <hi>in his Book</hi> de Conjugio Clericorum: <hi>And when I ſhall have begg'd thy pardon for the many faults <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou maiſt poſſibly find in the Compoſing, Tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing or Printing of theſe few ſheets. Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend to ſerve thee, <hi>T.H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 1. 1673.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:45578:9"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Pag. 10. line 6. for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lin. 8. aft <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, add <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 24. inſtead of Fryer <hi>Menolein,</hi> read <hi>Menotein.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 28. inſtead of <hi>married married,</hi> r. <hi>married perſons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 66. inſtead of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> read <hi>Maimony.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 74. In the Margin, for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> r. <hi>Demonſtration.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45578:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of Marriage.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD at firſt did not make a Pair, a <hi>Male</hi> and a <hi>Female,</hi> in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as he did of the reſt of living Creatures; but he made the one of the other, the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Man; and thus <hi>Male and Female created he them,</hi> for to continue the Species by propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to be a mutual help and comfort each to other. The Angels, which each fill a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and are <hi>à poſteriori</hi> Eternal, were not made <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female;</hi> and therefore the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, who fanſied their Deities, <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female,</hi> and worſhipped many Godds, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Goddeſſes, muſt be conceived to have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped dead Men and Women. The difference of the Sex was made for the ſupply or remedy of our Mortality.</p>
            <p>When we ſhall come to be like the Angels of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45578:10"/>Heaven, then we ſhall neither Marry, nor be given in Marriage. Meat, Drink, Cloathing, and Marriage, are all proviſions only for this ſtate. In the Regeneration, there ſhall be no further need or uſe of them.</p>
            <p>Our Creator made the Woman of the Man, to ſhew the near Union and Conjunction which ſhould be betwixt the Man and his Wife. 1. God himſelf made the Woman, as of the Man, ſo for the Man, for his Comfort and Benefit, and to be one fleſh with him. And ſince <hi>Adam</hi> had his Marriage ordained and celebrated by God himſelf in Paradiſe, and in the ſtate of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; Who are they that diſpute againſt God, againſt his Ordinance and Inſtitution? Such as of old, <hi>Montanus</hi> and <hi>Marcion,</hi> who condemned Marriage as uncleanneſs; and ſuch as St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> who ſpoke unbecomingly of it; ſuch as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who forbid Biſhops and Prieſts to Marry, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tolerate them the having of a <hi>Concubine</hi> than a <hi>Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot prefer the Woman before the Man abſolutely, although it be granted, ſhe was made after the Man, and of the Man, and not of the common Earth immediately. And that Anatomiſts tell us of a finer Structure in the Body of the Woman than of the Man. For the Holy Scripture tells us, That <hi>the Man was not made for the Woman, but the Woman for the Man;</hi> and therefore ſure the Man is the Head of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45578:10"/>the Woman, and to be preferred before her. The Light of Nature taught the very Heathens to prefer the <hi>Male</hi> before the <hi>Female.</hi> When the Poets would ſhame men, they call them <hi>Women.</hi> We read in <hi>Homer</hi>'s Illid. B. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In <hi>Virgil</hi> his Aeneids, B. <hi>9. O merè Phrygie nequae enim Phryges.</hi> So <hi>Perſius</hi> uſes the word <hi>Troiades,</hi> Sat. 1. inſtead of <hi>Trojani.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good reaſon then that Wives ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to their own Husband; and that that Law of <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> ſhould be an Oecumenial Law, <hi>viz. That every Man ſhould bear rule in his own houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt in Scripture, 'tis obſerved, gives three Reaſons of the ſubjection of the Wife to the Husband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Becauſe that <hi>Adam was firſt formed, then Eve;</hi> whereas other Creatures were created the Male and the Female together at the ſame time, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> Becauſe the Woman was made to be a meet help and comfort for the Man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Becauſe the Woman was made or built out of the Man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8.</p>
            <p>And as a ſign of the ſubjection that was due from the Wife to the Husband, the Women in Eaſtern Countries us'd to wear a Vail on their Heads, and over their Faces, and in ſo doing, the Wife was ſaid to have power on her Head,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45578:11"/>becauſe ſhe had a Vail, which did ſignifie that ſhe was under the power of her Husband, and therefore ſhe is commanded to fear her Husband, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.33. <hi>Which,</hi> ſaith Reverend Mr. <hi>Bains</hi> on that place, <hi>did meet with the lewdneſs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Women, that think it their glory to know no awe; for pleaſing, they ſtand on no ſuch points; if they like not, they may leave, ſay they, let them get others do it better; to their Husbands moved, they will not ſtick to bid them go walk themſelves: For fearing them they cannot; why ſhould they make ſuch bull-beggers of them, they are their Wives, not their Slaves? Should they be pointed at for Sheep all the Town over? Theſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Devil will round you in the ear with; But know, that you had better be God's Sheep, than the Devil's Shrews.</hi> — So he.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>John R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>binſon,</hi> in his Eſſayes, <hi>p.</hi> 126. ſaith, <hi>If the Husband paſs the bounds of wiſdom and kindneſs, yet muſt not ſhe ſhake off the bond of ſubmiſſion; but muſt bear patiently the burthen which God hath laid upon the Daughters of</hi> Eve. <hi>The Woman in innocency was to be ſubject to the Man, but this ſhould have been without all wrong on his part, or grief on hers; but ſhe being firſt in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, hath brought her ſelf under another ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and, the ſame to her grievor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in regard of her Husband, often unjuſt, but in regard of God, always moſt juſt; who hath ordained that her deſire ſhould be ſubject to her Husband, who by her ſeduction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45578:11"/>ſubject to him. And albeit, many proud Women think it a matter of ſcorn and diſgrace thus to humble themſelves to God and their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and even glory in the contrary; yet they but glory in their ſhame, and in their Husbands ſhame alſo; and whilſt they refuſe a croſs, chuſe a ſin of rebellion, both againſt God and their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. Which ſhall not eſcape unpuniſhed from God, though many fond Husbands nouriſh them therein, and by pampering and puffing them up by delicate Fare, coſtly Apparel, and Idleneſs, teach them to deſpiſe themſelves and all others.</hi> So far my Author.</p>
            <p>And let me here have leave to ſay, That the pride &amp; peeviſhneſs of ſome Wives to their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands in our dayes, hath brought an ill report on Matrimony; and 'tis to be feared, hath frighted many from the remedy of Marriage, into the Diſeaſe of Adultery and Uncleanneſs. If Wives would, by their diſcretion, and by their meck and quiet Spirits, they might gain their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands love and affection, and they might do this kindneſs for thoſe of their Sex that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, they would raiſe and quicken the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, ſo that Tradeſmen that are well ſtock'd with Daughters, ſhould not have cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that their Daughters are the verieſt Drug they have about them. Let the Wife make it her buſineſs to pleaſe her Husband in lawful things, and to the reſt of her Endowments, of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45578:12"/>Parts, Parentage, Beauty, Education, Portion, add that which makes the reſt, That they are not meer Cyphers in compariſon and account; namely, Let her ſtudy to frame and compoſe her ſelf what may be, <hi>viz.</hi> lawfully, to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, in conforming her Manners to his. And let not the Husband delight to domineer over his Wife, or pleaſe himſelf in ſhewing alwayes his Authority, <hi>(which none but fools will do,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>J. Robinſon). Nabal</hi> was, according to his Name, a very Fool, that was ſo churliſh, that neither Wife nor any body elſe could ſpeak to him. It was <hi>Abigails</hi> wiſdom to bear patiently with him; as it was the wiſdom of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that taught him to bear with his <hi>Zantippe,</hi> her daily home-brawlings, and thereby learned him to converſe quietly and patiently with unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, perverſe, and peeviſh perſons abroad.</p>
            <p>The Husband ſhould be able alway to guide, counſel, and direct the Wife, to go before her as a man of knowledge. <hi>His Wife he ſhould uſe as a Comfort and Helper, not,</hi> (ſaith Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh) as a Counſellor. When</hi> Adam <hi>in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency,</hi> (he obſerves) <hi>and</hi> Solomon, <hi>the wiſeſt of Temporal Princes, took counſel of their Wives, they both miſcarried; no ſuch wonder as lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then that other men have been ſo allured to ſo many inconvenient and wicked practices by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of their Wives, or other beloved Darlings. If</hi> Adam <hi>in the ſtate of perfection, and</hi> Solomon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45578:12"/>
               <hi>the Son of</hi> David, <hi>God's choſen Servant, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a man endowed with the greateſt wiſdom, did both of them diſobey their Creator by the inſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the love they bear to a Woman; It is not ſo wonderful,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that others have done the like.</hi> So he.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Marriage of Perſons in Holy Orders.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MArriage is honourable amongſt all; our Saviour graced a Wedding with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee, John</hi> 2. and there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted his Glory, by working that Miracle, of turning Water into Wine: By which thoſe who enter into that ſtate, might be put in mind, that their ſorrows ſhould be turned into joys. The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Epheſ. 5.32. makes Marriage a Myſtery, and to ſet out the relation and love 'twixt Chriſt and his Church. And laſtly, 'Tis thought Heaven is ſet out in Scripture by a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Feaſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. and the Joys of Heaven repreſented by the joys of a Wedding, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. The <hi>Nazarites</hi> that were whiter than Snow, by reaſon of their vow of Holineſs, were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed by their Marriage.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45578:13"/>
               <head>Of the Marriage of Prieſts.</head>
               <p>The High Prieſt under the Law, was not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to Marry, onely he muſt have a Wife ſo and ſo qualified. <hi>Aaron</hi> the High Prieſt, the Saint of the Lord, a Type of our Lord Chriſt, was Married, and the High Prieſt-hood annexed to his Family, and entail'd on his poſterity. It is made a Character of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> or <hi>Epimanes</hi> rather, that he ſhould not regard Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or deſire Women, in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.37. And 'tis made a mark of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and branded for a Doctrine of Devils, (according to our Tranſlators) to forbid to Marry in the New Teſtament, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 3. And as Prieſts and Prophets under the Law might lawfully marry, ſo might the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Miniſters of our Lord and Saviour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Goſpel. St. <hi>Peter</hi> the firſt, or chief of the Apoſtles, as to a primacy of Order, was of this Order himſelf. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſerts his right and power to lead about a Wife or Siſter, as well as <hi>Cephas</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> and other of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scripture foreſeeing</hi> (ſaith a Reverend Author) <hi>the frenſie of this Hereſie,</hi> (viz. <hi>of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding marriage to Prieſts) made the Wall higher and ſtronger, of the lawful marriage of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy; for beſides the places wherein generally it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45578:13"/>is (without all exception) permitted to all Orders of men to Marry; it ſpeaketh eſpecially of the lawful uſe of Marriage in the Miniſtry. It ſpeaks particularly of their Wives, likewiſe of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: which we remember not to be done in any other eſtates; onely of the Kings it is ſaid, That they ſhould not marry many Wives: Wherefore the Miniſters having not onely the common evidence which all other men have to hold their Wives by, but alſo certain Specialties, and ſpecial Charters, whereby the quiet and peaceable poſſeſſion of them is warranted, it is evident that the Popiſh Court, which impleadeth them, and condemneth them for their Wives, is a lawleſs Court.</hi> So Mr. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> in his Anſwer to the <hi>Rhem. Teſt. Annot.</hi> on St. <hi>Mat. chap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>And amongſt the Canons aſcribed to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, it is decreed, <hi>Can.</hi> 5. <hi>If any Biſhop, Elder, or Deacon, under colour of Religion, or reverence, put away his Wife, let him be ſeparate from his Miniſtry; if he abide in that mind, let him be depoſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Canon</hi> (ſaith the aforeſaid Author) <hi>is of a contrary ſpirit to you; for you ſever men from their Wives, that ſever themſelves to the Miniſtry; and it ſevereth men from the Miniſtry, that ſever themſelves from their Wives, under pretence of the Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> in his demonſtration of the <hi>Problem,</hi> teſtifies, <hi>That the Marriage of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45578:14"/>Clergy, for the ſpace of</hi> 300 <hi>years after Chriſt was a thing alwayes freely allowed without prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or vow of perpetual continency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Dracontius,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>And there are many of the Biſhops,</hi> ſaith <hi>Athanaſius, that have not married; and contrariwiſe, many Monks we ſee daily become Fathers of Children. Again you may obſerve many Biſhops to be Fathers of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and many Monks that have not ſought to ſee their own Generation; for this is lawful, and the other is not forbidden, but every one as he liketh, let him undertake to live. And whereas we read,</hi> ſaith the Decretal, <hi>c.</hi> 56. <hi>That the Sons of Prieſts have come to the honour of the Papacy, we muſt not underſtand them to be begotten by Fornication, but by lawful Marriage, which was lawful for the Prieſts every where, until the time of prohibition; and in the Eaſt Churches is lawful to this day; The ſingleneſs of Prieſt-hood was inſtituted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the poverty of the Churches wanting ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient means to maintain many families of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons.</hi> D. 28. c. d. Syr.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Siricius,</hi> about the year 385. forbad Prieſts Marriage in the Weſtern Church. But that Decree had no Univerſal Admiſſion in the Church until the time of Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> 1007.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45578:14"/>And 'tis obſerved that Biſhops and Prieſts mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in <hi>England</hi> until <hi>Anſelms</hi> time, that is, about 1100 years after Chriſt, no Law forbidding them. 'Tis an obſervation of <hi>Balſamon</hi> on the 5th Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Apoſtles, that it was lawful before the 6th Synod in <hi>Trullo,</hi> for the Biſhops to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and have Wives, yea after they had received that dignity. And for my part, I think, Arch-Biſhop <hi>Crammer</hi> the Martyr, no leſs a Saint, though once or twice married, then if he had lived ſingle. Arch-Biſhop <hi>Parker</hi> alſo, as I have read, was a married Man; and our Church, ſince the Reformation, never forbad any of her Fathers or Children to Marry, <hi>eo nomine,</hi> or elſe they could not be Presbyters, Prieſts, Biſhops, or Arch-Biſhops.</p>
               <p>It was ſmartly replyed by Dr. <hi>Featley,</hi> when ſome had charged it on the Puritans, that they were <hi>Calviniſtae tantum non in Sabbato,</hi> that their Adverſaries were <hi>Papiſtae tantum non in uxoratu.</hi> Certainly Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Cozens,</hi> were all Canonical Men, and yet all Married. And Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> was one of the firſt that for a while was thought to diſcountenance Marriage in men of Holy Orders, ſaying, <hi>That in diſpoſing of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Preferments, he would prefer the ſingle Man before the Married, ſuppoſing the Abilities of the Perſons were otherwiſe equal.</hi> But Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> that wrote his Life, tells us, by what means
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45578:15"/>and method, he ſought to procure other appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of him; namely, by negotiating, not long after, a Marriage between Mr. <hi>Thomas Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> one of his Chaplains, and a Daughter of <hi>Windebank,</hi> his old Friend; and he officiated the whole ſervice of their Marriage in his own Chappel, at <hi>London</hi>-Houſe, joyning their Hands, and giving the Nuptial Benediction, and perfecting all other Eccleſiaſtical Rites which belong to the Solemnization of Matrimony by the Rules of this Church. <hi>D. H. in his Life,</hi> p. 212.</p>
               <p>I acknowledge that the Papiſts urge againſt the Marriage of our Clergy, the ill manners and lives of their Children. I confeſs I cannot tell of any one of our married Clergyes Wives, that can match that Whore, who, they ſay, was the Mother of <hi>Gratian, Petrus Corneſtor,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lumbard;</hi> yet doubtleſs there have been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous men who have been Children of Biſhops, the Fathers of the Church, and of others in Holy Orders. Biſhop <hi>King,</hi> late of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> was the Son of Biſhop <hi>King,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> late of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> was the Son of Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> whoſe Works praiſe him in the Gate. And it hath been obſerved, that five Knightly Families deſcended from Arch-Biſhop <hi>Sands,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York.</hi> One of the greateſt blots in our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Biſhops Eſcutcheons in this matter is, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45578:15"/>Sir <hi>Toby Matthews,</hi> a great Son of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was a Son of Arch-Biſhop <hi>Matthews</hi> of <hi>York.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me add, for the honour of our Married Clergy, that Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> that famous Sea Captain, was the Son of a Miniſter in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many at this day have attained to the honour of Knighthood, who owe their Eſtates to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Arch-Biſhops: And 'tis no abatement to their Honour, that the late reverend and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Bp. of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Bp. <hi>Wilkins,</hi> his Mother was the Daughter of a Miniſter, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>John Dod,</hi> a man famous in his Generation for Piety, and a learned Man, and who taught that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Critick of <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and the great Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Hebrew.</p>
               <p>It cannot be denyed, that moſt of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Writers cry up the excellency of Virginity; and that divers of the Fathers pleading for the ſingleneſs of Prieſts, do detract from the due praiſes of Marriage.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Siricius</hi> ſtuck not to ſay, <hi>That they that are in the fleſh, that is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in Matrimony, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Ambroſe, Offic. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap. ult.</hi> will have the Prieſts to be pure from Marriage, and to be contaminated by Marriage. But the bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> a greater than theſe, allows a Biſhop to be the Husband of one Wife, that is,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45578:16"/>one who liveth chaſtly with one Wife alone at one time. And whereas ſome would oppoſe Marriage and Chaſtity, the ſame Apoſtle, in <hi>Titus</hi> 2.4, &amp; 5. teaches us, that Wedlock and Chaſtity are not divorced or ſeparated each from other, but may dwell together in the ſame Houſe and the ſame Boſom, exhorting <hi>Titus, to teach the young Women to be ſober, to love their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, to love their Children; to be diſcreet, chaſt, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</hi> That which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>That 'tis good for a man not to touch a Woman,</hi> is to be interpreted, 'Tis not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, <hi>viz.</hi> that if a man have the gift of continency, and with particular reſpect to the Chriſtian Church in that time of Perſecution; for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>Nevertheleſs to avoid Fornication, let every Man have his own Wife, and let every Woman have her own Husband,</hi> Verſ. 2. of the ſame Chapter.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> a good Man, and a Biſhop in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> though himſelf a ſingle Perſon, named an honeſt Matrimonial Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>a Godly Chaſtity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Celibaty,</hi> or ſingle-Life of the Clergy, and others in the Popedom, hath hindred much good, and given great occaſion to abominable ſins.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lrich,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> in an Epiſtle which he wrote, complained of a fearful Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle at <hi>Rome;</hi> namely, that after Pope <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45578:16"/>had decreed and confirmed the unmarried kind of Life, he intended to fiſh in a deep Pond at <hi>Rome,</hi> hard by the Monaſtery of the Nuns; the Water of the Pond being let out, they found more than ſix thouſand Heads of Children, which had been caſt into the Pond and drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; theſe were the fruits of the unmarried life: Whereupon Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> amazed at the ſight, aboliſhed that Decree concerning the unmarried kind of life; but the ſucceeding Popes decreed the ſame again.</p>
               <p>And in the Monaſtry of <hi>Neuburgh</hi> in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> where there had been Nuns who were diſplaced for their ungodly leacherous doings, as my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſaith, when the <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryers, who were ſet therein, intending to build, digged up twelve great Pots, in each Pot was a Carcaſe of a little Child.</p>
               <p>We are told, that the Multitude of Baſtards are ſo great at <hi>Rome,</hi> that they are conſtrained to build particular Monaſtries, wherein they are brought up, and that the Pope is named their Father; and that when any great Proceſſions are held in <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſaid Baſtards go all before the Pope. If the Pope be accounted Father to all the Baſtards, that may call the Whore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> Mother, I ſuppoſe he may have as many Children every day in the year, as that Counteſs had at a Birth, namely, as many as there are dayes in the year.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45578:17"/>
               <p>Our Hiſtories tell us, That <hi>John de Crema,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Italian</hi> Cardinal, was ſent over from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> with his bigneſs and bravery, to bluſter our Engliſh Clergy out of their Wives, he made, 'tis ſaid, a moſt gaudy Oration in the commendation of Virginity; and on the ſame Night at <hi>London</hi> he was caught in Bed with a Harlot. See <hi>F. H.</hi> B. 3. p. 23. But the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal might far ſooner and eaſier be permitted his Concubine or Harlot, than the Engliſh Clergy their lawful Wives, the Pope being Judge.</p>
               <p>We find afterwards, that the Clergy paying a Fee or Fine to the Pope, were tolerated their Concubines: And this cuſtom was ſo general, and thought ſo juſtifiable, that when one of the Prieſts pleaded he had no Concubine, it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſtrait, <hi>Habeat ſi velit, ſolvat pecuniam,</hi> He may have one if he will, let him pay his Money.</p>
               <p>Yea, it has of late dayes been maintained, That Marriage in a Clergy-Man, is a greater ſin than Fornication, if not than Adultery; and yet their Schoolmen, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Scotus,</hi> that in other things differ, agree in this, <hi>That the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life of Prieſts, is not by Scripture prohibited, but by the Conſtitutions of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſhall we ſay to theſe Men that make it a greater ſin to break the Law of the Church, than the Commandments of God? Sure we are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Scripture prohibits the Marriage of Prieſts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45578:17"/>or Miniſters of the Church. The Apoſtles were no more enjoyned to forſake their Wives, than their Father and Mother, Houſe and Land; and that ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>That whoſoever did forſake father or mother, or houſe and land, or wife for his ſake,</hi> reſpected thoſe that were not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as well as them that were. 'Tis well noted by our Church Hiſtorian, that <hi>Enoch walked with God, and begat ſons and daughters: In which Enoch,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>met the threefold capacity of King, Prieſt and Prophet:</hi> He made not a Prayer the leſs for having a child the more; and let us be but alike holy with <hi>Enoch,</hi> and let others be more holy with <hi>Anſelm</hi> and <hi>Dunſtan,</hi> that oppoſed the marriage of the Clergy here in <hi>England.</hi> They ſay of the latter, that <hi>he took the Devil by the noſe;</hi> how true that is I know not, but in this point, <hi>forbidding to marry,</hi> being a <hi>doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> 'tis true enough, that the <hi>Devil led him by the noſe.</hi> If that place be urged, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.33. where the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>he that is married careth for the things of the world, how he may pleaſe his wife.</hi> The Hiſtorian anſwers, <hi>Theſe things are</hi> vitia m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iti, <hi>not</hi> matrimonli; uxoris, <hi>not</hi> uxoratus, <hi>flowing neither from the exerciſe of marriage, but only from the depraved uſe thereof, which by Gods aſſiſtance and mans beſt endeavours, may be rectified and amended.</hi> So he.</p>
               <p>That other ſaying of the Apoſtle in the ſame Chapter, <hi>Defrand ye not one another, except it be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45578:18"/>with conſent, for a time, that ye may give your ſelves to faſting and prayer, and come together again, that Satan tempt you not, by reaſon of your not having the gift of continency,</hi> doth not juſtifie the Popiſh Prohibition of marriage; for that Interdiction of the Marriage-bed is voluntary, by mutual conſent of the parties, and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary only, <hi>durante bene placito:</hi> But the Popiſh Prohibition is impulſive, by the power of others; and perpetual, to continue during their lives, <hi>F.H.b.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 22. Wo to them by whom ſo great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and ſcandals come, as do daily in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, from the forbidding to marry. If marriage be a Sacrament, why ſhould the Prieſt be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the uſe of it? and if it be uncleanneſs, as the <hi>Marcionites</hi> and <hi>Manichees</hi> taught, why are the common people, the Laity indulged it? There were, I know, the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.12. <hi>ſome that made themſelves Eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven:</hi> But our Saviour hath laid upon his Diſciples, whether Miniſters or ordinary Chriſtians, no ſuch unneceſſary bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. If a man have the gift of continency, which is not a common, but a proper gift, he may receive it, but not in <hi>Origens</hi> ſenſe, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorized other Scriptures, and 'tis ſaid, took this in a literal ſenſe; by the ſame reaſon we ſhould cut off our right hands, and pluck out our right eyes, and diſmember our ſelves, and deſtroy our bodies, leſt they ſhould be occaſions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45578:18"/>and inſtruments of ſin to us: But this way of interpreting thoſe ſayings of Chriſt in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, would be contradictory to God's Law, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sixth Commandment. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith indeed, <hi>Mortifie your members which are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth,</hi> which he expounds to be <hi>fornication, uncleanneſs, evil concupiſcence,</hi> &amp;c. But whilſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would compell her Prieſts and Nuns to be like the Angels of Heaven, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther marrying, nor giving in marriage,</hi> 'tis too apparent, they occaſion many to be worſe than Beaſts, and to be delivered over to the unclean Spirit, or to be poſſeſſed with an unclean De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
               <p>It is marked, that thoſe who have neglected the remedy of marriage, which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, have in vain uſed other means and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of cure. In vain, as to the cure of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, did St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſtrike his breaſt with ſtones, St. <hi>Francis</hi> embrace and kiſs the ſnow, to cool himſelf, and quench this fire of Luſt; and St. <hi>Benedict</hi> ſtrip himſelf naked, and lie among the thorns. In vain do the Romiſh Prieſts and Nuns make Vows oſ <hi>Celibacy,</hi> or Single-life; they Vow that which is not in their power, that is, to live always ſingle, and yet chaſtely; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the gift of continency is a proper gift, and rarely given. If they ſay, they will pray for this gift. But where hath God promiſed to hear ſuch prayers, it not being neceſſary to ſalvation to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45578:19"/>live chaſtely, without uſing the remedy. God gave not this gift to thoſe he loved dearly, to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Aaron,</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> tell us, that all the Apoſtles except <hi>John,</hi> were married; <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt had four Daughters; and <hi>Platina</hi> in the Life of <hi>Cletus</hi> the firſt, ſaith, that St. <hi>Luke</hi> was married, and that his wife was in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis a fond ſaying, an imagination of theſe mens brains, that the Apoſtles had wives, but that after their undertaking the Office of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, they never accompanied with them; they may as well ſay, they left for ever all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in their children, in their houſes, in their fiſher-boats: But we ſee that they did not, St. <hi>John</hi> had his houſe, wherein he entertained the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> after the death of our Saviour.</p>
               <p>Again; as to the Vows of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Nuns,</hi> ordinarily they are made unwillingly, or without knowledge of what they do, and whether they ſhall have power to contain. Men make their daughters Nuns at twelve years of age, and their ſons Monks at fourteen, when they know not what Concupiſcence meaneth, and which after kindling, burns more violently, like cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders covered over with aſhes, at laſt break out violently into a flame. Witneſs the unchaſte lives of many that are under this Vow of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45578:19"/>But <hi>if they cannot contain, it is better</hi> for them <hi>to marry than to burn;</hi> better break an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and unlawful Vow, than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God; better a Prieſt, or Monk, or Nun, their Vow notwithſtanding, marry, than to break the Commandments of God, and their Vow in Baptiſm. 'Tis horrid to think that the Popes forbid marriage, and permit or tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fornication and adultery in their Prieſts as a leſs crime than marriage.</p>
               <p>Again, That although a man that hath had two Wives, be accounted irregular in the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yet he that hath had divers Concubines is not, as Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> III. declareth. If for the ſtrengthning of their unlawful Vows, they urge that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.11, 12. where he ſaith, <hi>Refuſe the young widows; for when they have begun to wax wanton againſt Chriſt, they will marry; having damnation, becauſe they have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their firſt faith.</hi> This may be anſwered from the context, namely, that younger widows ſhould marry, and guide the houſe, and not be received into the Office of Deaconeſſes, of being ſervants to the Church, to relieve or look to the ſick, and to ſuccour the poor, becauſe ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if they ſhould make ſuch a promiſe to the Church, to continue in that ſtate all the days of their life, would be apt to break it, either by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wanton againſt Chriſt, committing fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or elſe would be under the power of their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45578:20"/>husband, and ſo not be at liberty to ſerve the Church. Now therefore the Apoſtle concludes, that none ſhould be received into the Church as Deaconeſſes, under the age of threeſcore, at which time, ſaith one, the Vow of not marrying would be ridiculous. <hi>Therefore the Pope and his Clergy,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Fulk, admitting other widows or virgins to profeſs or vow Continency, do ſin againſt the expreſs Commandment of the H. Ghoſt. Nor was the want of Monaſteries, and Monkiſh and Nuniſh Rules and Orders in the Apoſtles times, the occaſion of this Prohibition or reſtraint: For,</hi> ſaith my Author, <hi>the Incontinency of Nuns and Monks in Cloyſters, and under all your Rules and Orders, hath and doth daily give ſufficient proof, that Luſt will not be kept out by the walls of your Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, nor by the Rules and Preſcripts of your Orders. So then as the experience of ſome younger widows that had followed after Satan, was a ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to cauſe the Apoſtle to refuſe all young widows to the Office of Deaconeſſes; ſo the experience of ſo many Milch Nuns, and filthy Monks and Friers, teach us, that no young perſons are to be admitted to any Vow or Profeſſion of perpetual Continency.</hi> Let me add here what the ſaid Doctor hath out of <hi>Wierus de Praeſtig. Daemon. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9, 11. <hi>edit.</hi> 3. <hi>That the Devil helpeth the Nuns in their abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble luſts, in divers Nunneries in</hi> Germany, <hi>namely, in the Province of</hi> Colen, <hi>where the Devil in the likeneſs of a Dog, was ſeen to fall upon them in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45578:20"/>the day time, in moſt beaſtly manner, about the year of our Lord,</hi> 1558. <hi>alſo in the Nunnery of</hi> Nazanth <hi>in</hi> Colen, <hi>the Nuns in moſt filthy manner, ſuffered the ſame illuſion oftentimes, in the ſight and preſence of many,</hi> anno 1564.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſtate of the Church,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gerſon</hi> Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>Paris, is grown altogether bruitiſt and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous; and ſhould give an</hi> Item <hi>to the Overſeers to enquire, whether the Cloyſters of Nuns, be not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Stews of Harlots — and who would think,</hi> ſaith the Author of the Triumph of <hi>Rome</hi> over deſpiſed Proteſtancy, that <hi>ſo wiſe a man as</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius Branchedorus <hi>could ſo far over-reach as to ſay, that the luſts of whoredom and gluttony, and other ſhameful enormities, had gotten ſuch a head, that young men did</hi> pati muliebria, <hi>and Prieſts did</hi> facere virilia; <hi>and that their Nuns did, as it were, openly profeſs unchaſtity; and at laſt, that whoſoever was noted to be a ſhameleſs Adulterer, or a wild Ruffian, that had laviſh'd out all his Patrimony,</hi> anu, pene, ventre, <hi>was ſure to betake himſelf to the Court of</hi> Rome <hi>as his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.</hi> And again, <hi>Who could have looked for ſuch language to fall from ſo grave an Author</hi> as <hi>Eſpencaeus, that our Anceſtors wiſh'd, that our Clerks ſhould turn their wives into their ſiſters; but now our age turns them into Lemmans and Whores, and conſequently their lawful iſſue into Baſtards.</hi> And again, <hi>God hath taken away our ſons, and the Devil hath given us Nephews; and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45578:21"/>could imagine that ſo learned and ingenious a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n as</hi> Eraſmus <hi>would ſo far wrong his neighbours, as to ſay, that a number of Monaſteries are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, that the Stews are more chaſte, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and modeſt then they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſupplication of Beggars tender'd to King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. aſſured him, that by virtue of the Sacred Votaries, there were a hundred thouſand Whores in this our Nation. Fryar <hi>Menolem</hi> in the Pulpit cryed to the Clergy, <hi>Ye my Maſters of the Church, do not damn your ſouls: Ye have now Birds in the Cage that chirp to you by night; yt know my meaning, put them away.</hi> So the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Romes Triumph over deſpiſed Proteſtancy,</hi> which ſome ſay was Biſhop <hi>Hall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Church Hiſtorian tells us, that King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s fury fell moſt fiercely on the Dean and Canons of <hi>Pauls,</hi> for croſſing him in the choice of their Biſhop; for he ſent and took their <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caria's,</hi> that is (<hi>Roger Hoveden</hi> being Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) their <hi>Concubines,</hi> and caſt them into the <hi>Tower of London;</hi> where they continued many days, not without much ſcorn and diſgrace, till at laſt thoſe Canons ranſom'd their liberty at a great rate, <hi>F. Hiſt. Book</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>From theſe premiſes, I hope we may ſafely draw this good and honeſt Concluſion, That marriage is not to be prohibited to a whole Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of men within the pale of the Church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly, nor by conſequence; and that 'tis
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45578:21"/>not expedient to ſuffer young men, and young maids or women to vow <hi>Celibacy</hi> all their lives.</p>
               <p>It was piouſly ſaid of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond, <hi>That for great cauſes Prieſts wives were taken from them, but that for greater cauſes they ought to be reſtored to them again:</hi> See <hi>Platina</hi> in the life of the ſaid Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is better to marry than to burn,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and the Canons of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, had much better have had Wives than <hi>Focaria's,</hi> Fire-makers, or Concubines.</p>
               <p>How horrible is it that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth hold, <hi>That 'tis much better, and leſs offence, for a Prieſt to uſe another mans wife, than to marry one of his own, after that he hath once accepted and married our dear Mother the holy Church for his wife during life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But leaving ſuch <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Doctrine of the Romiſh Church, I come to the Canon of the holy Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. <hi>To avoid fornication, let everyman</hi> (and therefore Spiritual perſons are not exempted) <hi>have his own wife, and every wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (and therefore Nuns are not interdicted) <hi>have her own husband,</hi> and to avoid fornication it is enjoyned; and therefore all perſons of both Sexes, who have not the gift of Continency, are bound to marry; nor can any Vow or Oath be <hi>vinculum iniquitatis, i. e.</hi> a Bond of Iniquity, and oblige againſt God's Law, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery;</hi> and, <hi>It is better to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45578:22"/>marry than to burn.</hi> Beſides, if two Oaths be taken, and the one contradict the other, the firſt is obligatory, and not the ſecond. Now all Prieſts and Nuns in Baptiſm vowed to keep all God's Commandments, and therefore the Seventh, <hi>not to commit Adultery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe Scriptures, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy;</hi> and, <hi>Pray continually,</hi> concern all Chriſtians, as well as Prieſts and Profeſſed perſons; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they be interpreted to oblige from mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, they oblige the Laity as well as the Clergy, to uſe the ordinary diſtinction. Beſides, <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, though married perſons, were daily both morning and evening to attend upon the Sacrifice, and to burn Incenſe every morning, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.7. and this Incenſe was a Type of Prayer, which every Chriſtian, whether mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or ſingle, is bound to offer up unto God daily. As for holineſs, Matrimony is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with holineſs, witneſs <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Aaron</hi> the ſervant of the Lord, and <hi>Enoch</hi> that walked with God, and yet did not forſake his wife and children; and 'tis obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the <hi>Boſom of Abraham,</hi> although a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſon, is uſed to ſet out Heaven by in the Scripture. If Heaven had been ſet out by the Boſom of any Saint in Heaven, that had always led a ſingle life on earth, what triumphs would <hi>Rome</hi> have made on that occaſion. And whereas 'tis ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Thoſe that follow the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45578:22"/>Lamb whitherſoever he goeth, theſe are they which are not defiled with women, for they are Virgins.</hi> Certainly Chriſt is followed whitherſoever he goeth, not only by the bleſſed Saints that have led a ſingle life, but alſo by married perſons, as Patriarchs, Apoſtles, Martyrs, and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble others, as the Scripture ſpeaketh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. And the Apoſtle ſpeaks of all kind of true Believers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. Theſe are bought from among men, to be firſt-fruits unto God and the Lamb; theſe are dedicated, as firſt-fruits uſed to be, unto God. They are called ('tis thought) <hi>Virgins,</hi> becauſe they adhered to Chriſt, when the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> had made all the Kings and Nations of the earth drunk with the cup of her fornication. It is conceived this place may have reference to thoſe Iſraelites that were inticed to Idolatry by the Midianitiſh women; and 'tis frequent in Scripture to call, or compare Idolatry to Adultery or Fornication; becauſe God's people are betrothed and married unto him, he is their Husband, and they his Spouſe, and when they go after Idols, they are ſaid to give God a Bill of divorce, and to go a whoring after other gods. Or, as Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> on the place, <hi>Theſe are they which had kept pure from all the heretical Gnoſtick corruptions of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs.</hi> Where there is neither ſpiritual nor carnal Fornication or Adultery, there is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing with women; for the marriage-bed in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45578:23"/>Scripture-Dialect is the bed undefiled, and <hi>to the pure all things are pure. The unbelieving hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, is ſanctified by the believing wife; and the unbelieving wife, by the believing husband, and therefore are their children holy.</hi> If marriage was filthineſs, or uncleanneſs, or a vice, or that married perſons could not pleaſe God, doubtleſs the H. Ghoſt would never have ſaid, <hi>Marriage is honorable amongst all,</hi> and therefore amongſt Clergy men; nor would our bleſſed Saviour have been born of a Mother, though a Virgin, yet eſpouſed and married to a husband, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Joſeph. Marriage,</hi> one ſaith, <hi>fills earth, and Virginity heaven;</hi> but if there were no Saints in earth, how ſhould there be any in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? if earth were empty, how could heaven be full of Saints? He did not commend his Sex that ſaid, a woman was a neceſſary evil, for how evil then muſt man be deemed, for whom ſuch an evil is neceſſary? and I take him to be a fool as well as mad, that being asked, whether he was married? he anſwered, <hi>He was never ſo mad yet;</hi> for I dare ſay, there are more made ſober than mad by marriage. I preſume, that Hypochondriacal Melancholy, a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, doth more ſeiſe and diſtract ſingle, than married married perſons. And confident I am, as one ſaith, that the Patriarchs did converſe with many wives more chaſtely, than many do now adays with one; ſo that many live now
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45578:23"/>more holily and chaſtely in Wedlock, than others in their Cloyſters and Cells. And if when a voyce from heaven calls to ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether man or woman, whether Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical or Temporal perſons, <hi>Let every man have his own wife,</hi> &amp;c. Let them not ſay or reply, I do not meddle with any ſtate that is common or unclean. If they ſhould, I reply to them again, <hi>What God hath cleanſed,</hi> or rather always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a pure, holy and undefiled eſtate, that <hi>call not thou common or unclean.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Qualifications requiſite in them that marry.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS for the Qualifications of a Husband or Wife, I would adviſe all to look at <hi>true Religion</hi> in the firſt place, that thoſe that marry, may be ſaid to marry in the Lord. If I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake not, this was that King <hi>James</hi> adviſed Prince <hi>Henry</hi> unto, <hi>v.</hi> B.Δ. 2 <hi>b.p.</hi> 72. &amp;c. When <hi>Solomon</hi> married the Daughters of a ſtrange god, then he fell to tolerate, if not to worſhip their Idols.</p>
            <p>Next to Religion, I ſhould commend a <hi>Suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Diſpoſition,</hi> and a <hi>Conformity in Manners,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:45578:24"/>that man and wife may delight in the ſociety and converſe one of another. And as I would not have a man or woman marry meerly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chiefly by their eyes or fancies; ſo neither would I adviſe a marriage betwixt thoſe that have an averſneſs or antipathy at firſt ſight each to other. I would have a natural, free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforced affection before marriage. When there is no other affection 'twixt parties than what is the fruit of <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> or <hi>Syllogiſms,</hi> I would never perſwade a marriage: Syllogiſtical love, ſuch as is raiſed thus:
<list>
                  <item>Every man muſt love his wife:</item>
                  <item>But this woman is my wife;</item>
                  <item>Therefore I ought to love her.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo on the part of the woman in reference to her husband.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Every woman muſt love her own husband:</item>
                  <item>This man is my husband;</item>
                  <item>Therefore I muſt love him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, this love goes ſo far about, that it is like to be long before it bring home affections. Nature is always at hand, and natural affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are up at firſt view; but Reaſon, Religion and Grace too, are ſometimes to ſeek, or held off at diſtance by Paſſion. 'Tis true notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45578:24"/>that thoſe that match meerly by the eye, many times meet with their match, an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore, or a very thorn in their eye; and that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which was a Loadſtone to attract their love, proves a ſnare to others, and a torment to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whilſt it draws others eyes to the ſame object, and occaſions jealouſie. And if neither of theſe happen, as oftentimes both do, yet a diſeaſe, a ſickneſs, or at leaſt old age changes the beautiful <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, into a <hi>Chaos;</hi> and the moſt <hi>lovely countenance,</hi> into an object in which thou wilt ſay, <hi>I have no pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, let me adviſe you not to marry by the ear, not for honor, or great parentage, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Titles; for theſe without virtue and money, are of ſmall value, an empty ſound, a tinkling cymbal, yea, more diſcord than harmony for the moſt part in ſuch matches, and hence ordinarily is the worſt ſort of marriage-muſick. Impari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in birth and parentage makes odds, where all ſhould be even; the one oft lords it in this caſe, and the other is but a ſervant, and a ſervant to to their fellow yoke-fellow, a ſervant, underling to all their high kindred, and often deſpiſed by their own ſervants. 'Tis in ſuch families oft as 'tis in the Family of Hawks, the males are the underlings, and the females have the reſpect, the glory, the maſtery.</p>
            <p>I ſhould further adviſe, not to marry by the hand or weight, meerly for money: To marry
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45578:25"/>World or Mammon, this is next to marrying the Devil. 'Tis true, a wiſe Counſellor adviſed his Son <hi>to marry a wife with ſomething, becauſe nothing could be bought in the Market without money:</hi> Yet a mateh <hi>meerly</hi> for money, is not of Gods making, nor mans making, God never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, nor ever approved of ſuch matches; and I have ſeen a Picture of three marriages, one ſaid to be made by God, another by Love, and a third by the Devil, and this third in the Picture was, when two old covetous wretches married together, that they might joyn houſe to houſe, land to land, and bag to bag. It was well obſerved by Mr. <hi>Herbert Palmer,</hi> in his lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle piece of making Religion ones buſineſs, that he never found in all the Scriptures, amongſt all the ends of marriage, that God ordained mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to make one rich. And if ſo, then if we will make that the chief end of marriage, which was never by our Maker and the Author of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, intended or deſigned any end at all, how much are we degenerated! how have we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded our ſelves, and ſunk Gods Ordinance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to earth, mire and dirt! If I miſtake not, the <hi>Jews,</hi> and our Anceſtors the <hi>Saxons,</hi> uſed to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe their wives with gifts or dowries: Hence the cuſtom with us, of laying Gold and Silver upon the Book, in the Solemnization of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and the Miniſter's giving it to the Bride; and perhaps alſo thoſe words in the Office ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45578:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>on the mans part, <hi>with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> goods I thee endow;</hi> and the money given at that time, was an earneſt of the reſt. A good wife at any rate, is a good bargain. I had much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give money to buy a wife, then ſell my ſelf to purchaſe a rich one. <hi>Intolerabili nihil eſt quam faemina dives:</hi> he that marries for 100 s. &amp; 1000 s. a 100, a 1000 to one but he is overwiv'd. As he that marries above himſelf for honour, is like a ſhip that hath too much ſail for its ballaſt; ſo he that marries below himſelf for money, is like a ſhip over-laden, that hath too much burthen for its ſails, and ſo is in danger of ſinking. <hi>They that will be rich, fall into temptation, and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and dangerous luſts, which drown men in perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, marry neither only or chiefly for beauty, by the eye; nor for honour, by the ear; nor for money or wealth, by the hand; but find out a meet helper, a ſuitable yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, one whom you are ſure you ſhall love, becauſe you do love her, and that too for her Virtues and Qualifications, ſo decently lodged, that you cannot but be pleaſed to dwell with them.</p>
            <p>To conclude this particular about the choice of a wife, and converſation with a wife, let me mind you what Wiſdom it ſelf adviſeth, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>To marry in the Lord,</hi> A woman that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, of a meek and quiet ſpirit, in whoſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45578:26"/>lips is the Law of kindneſs, in whom your heart can ſafely truſt, a good houſewife, that will look well to the ways of her houſhold, and will not eat the bread of idleneſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>And that you may hope for ſuch a bleſſing, the greateſt earthly felicity; for your prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to marriage, take King <hi>James</hi> his advice to his Son Prince <hi>Henry, Keep your body clean and unpolluted, till you give it to your wife, to whom only it belongeth; for how can you juſtly crave to be joyned to a pure Virgin, if your body be pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted? why ſhould the one half be clean, and the other defiled?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the time of your marriage, defer not to marry till your old age; for marriage was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to quench the luſt of youth. Marry not a woman unable, either through age, nature or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident for procreation of children; neither mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of known evil conditions, or vicious edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for the woman is ordained to be a <hi>helper,</hi> and not a <hi>hinderer</hi> to man. Add hereunto as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, as that wife Prince adviſeth, if they may be had, <hi>Beauty, Riches,</hi> and <hi>Friendſhip by Alliance</hi> in your marriage; becauſe Beauty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth your love to your wife, contenting you the better with her, without caring for others; and Riches and great Alliance, do both make her the abler to be a helper to you: Marry eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to one of your own Religion, weigh and conſider how you and your wife can be one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45578:26"/>fleſh, and keep unity betwixt you, being mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of two oppoſite Churches: Diſagreement in Religion brings on with it, diſagreement in manners. <hi>When you are married,</hi> ſaith the Royal Author, <hi>keep inviolably your promiſe made to God in your marriage; and for your behaviour to your wife, the Scripture can beſt give you counſel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Treat her as your own fleſh, command her as her Lord, cheriſh her as your helper, rule her as your pupil, and pleaſe her in all things reaſonable, but teach her not to be curious in things that belongs her not. Ye are the head, ſhe is the body; it is your Office to command, and hers to obey, but yet with ſuch a ſweet harmony, as ſhe ſhould be as ready to obey, as you to command; as willing to follow, as ye to go before: Your love being wholly knit unto her, and all her affections lovingly bent to follow your will.</hi> Three Rules he eſpecially gives the Prince concerning his wife; <hi>Hold her at the Oeconomick Rule of the houſe, and yet all to be ſubject to your direction — Keep carefully good and chaſte company about her; for women are the fraileſt Sex — And be never both angry at once, but when you ſee her in paſſion, you ſhould with reaſon danton yours.</hi> B.Δ. 2 <hi>b. p.</hi> 82.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:45578:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONe great end of Marriage, is the peopling the world with mankind, eſpecially plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church with a holy Seed; becauſe men and women, the individuals, dye, they ſeek law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and rationally, by marriage, the conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their kind; and becauſe men cannot avoid death, and live ever here, they ſeek to live after death in their poſterity; when they are dead in their own perſons, they have a kind of Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in their children. Good and bad, Saints and ſinners, and thoſe of both Sexes too, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of children; <hi>What wilt thou give me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Abraham, ſeeing I go childleſs? and this Eliezar of Damaſcus, a ſtranger, born in my houſe, is my heir;</hi> and, <hi>Give me children or elſe I dye,</hi> ſaid <hi>Rachel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Encreaſe and multiply,</hi> was one of Gods firſt bleſſings to his Creatures, after their firſt creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Fruitfulneſs</hi> is generally reckoned a <hi>bleſſing,</hi> as <hi>Barrenneſs</hi> a <hi>curſe</hi> in the holy Scripture. God our heavenly Father, that hath the key of the clouds, he keeps the key of the womb: he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb, that ſhe conceived a Son in her old
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45578:27"/>age, and he faſt ſhut up all the wombs in <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi>'s Court. Hence it is, that children are an inheritance of the Lord, and that it is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of God's prerogatives, that he maketh the barren woman to keep houſe, and to be a joyful mother of children. And therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Patriarchs and Saints of the Lord were thus perſwaded, they made their humble addreſſes and petitions at the Throne of Grace for children.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, that <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> put up their joynt prayers to God for a Son; ſo did <hi>Hannab</hi> the Mother of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and we may probably gueſs, <hi>Zachary</hi> the Father of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> whilſt he miniſtred in the Temple and prayed; for we read, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.18. the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Fear not, Zacharias, for thy prayer is heard, and thy wife Elizabeth, ſhall bear thee a ſon, and thou ſhalt call his name</hi> John: And truly, if God give a child in anſwer to prayers, 'tis to be hoped, that ſuch child will anſwer the Parents prayers, and prove a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; and ſo did <hi>Iſaac, Samuel</hi> and <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi> I confeſs, that ſometimes wicked men, who are deſcribed to be ſuch, as call not upon God, have their fill of children, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14. and again, that <hi>they ſend forth their children like a flock;</hi> yea, <hi>and their children dance,</hi> Job 21.11. But yet I ſay, that children that are the fruit of prayers, are uſually a double bleſſing; when as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45578:28"/>children beſtowed on wicked Parents, who pray not for them, oft-times prove a diſmal curſe to them. In the one ſort, God, as it were, lights in his ſervants Families a Candle, that their names be not put out in obſcurity: In the other, he permits a fire to be kindled, and that to a kind of wild-fire, which ſoon conſumes the whole houſe, with the timber thereof, and the ſtones thereof. 'Tis a bleſſing to be fruitful, and to have our name continued; on the contrary, 'tis a curſe to be barren, and to have our names blotted out; and therefore God provided, that if the elder Brother dyed childleſs, the next Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was to raiſe up ſeed unto his Brother, and that was to be called after his Brothers name.</p>
            <p>The cauſes of Barrenneſs, are oft-times:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Diſobedience to Parents:</hi> 'Tis juſt and equal that they ſhould dye childleſs, that do not honour their Parents, by whom, under God, they had their own Beings, Births and Lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Adultery and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs:</hi> Thoſe who lie with other mens wives, are puniſhed with Barrenneſs in their own wives.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Notorious Wickedneſs, and obſtinate Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt God:</hi> When a man is wicked over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, well may God in wrath ſay, <hi>Write this man Childleſs,</hi> or, there ſhall no more of this mans ſeed be ſown; and <hi>Job</hi> 18.19. <hi>He ſhall neither have ſon nor nephew among his people, not any remaining in his dwelling.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:45578:28"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>An inordinate deſire of great things in this world, and of the continuance of our Name and Family,</hi> Pſal. 49.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Perſecuting of Gods Saints and Servants, or afflicting the poor and needy,</hi> Pſal. 109.13. <hi>Let his poſterity be cut off, let his name be wiped out.</hi> Certainly on the other ſide, Fruitfulneſs is a bleſſing; and as a good Wife is the beſt Earthly bleſſing without us, ſo are Children a ſpecial gift of God. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.9. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.3, 4. <hi>Children are an heritage of</hi> Jehovah; <hi>the fruit of the womb his reward,</hi> or <hi>wages.</hi> Hebr. As Barrenneſs is threatned and inflicted ſometimes as a curſe, ſo is Fruitfulneſs promiſed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed as a bleſſing; and yet God will be ſought unto for this bleſſing. So did <hi>Abraham</hi> ſeek God for a Son, and obtained him: After <hi>Iſaac</hi> had lived with his wife twenty years childleſs, they both (ſay the Jews) went to the Mount <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah,</hi> and prayed there for a child, and God heard them.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not adviſe <hi>Polygamy,</hi> as a means to be fruitful, and to multiply our Progeny. One wife ſeems enough, and often too much for one man to govern; and 'tis obſerved, that ſome who have allowed or indulged themſelves the liberty or licence of many Wives, have had the feweſt Children. <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Wives and Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines made up a thouſand, and yet we read but of three Children he had by them all.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:45578:29"/>
            <p n="2">2. Next to Prayer for Children, let me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe a ſerious reſolution to bring up your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which God ſhall beſtow on you, in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; reſolve you and your Children will ſerve the Lord. Endeavour to be able to ſay to God at laſt, when you come to give account of theſe Talents, <hi>Of all thou haſt given me, have I loſt none:</hi> There is never a ſon or daughter of perdition amongſt them, not a <hi>profane Eſau,</hi> or a <hi>curſed Cham,</hi> nor a <hi>ſcoffing Iſhmael,</hi> never a <hi>wandering Dinah,</hi> nor a <hi>mocking Michal;</hi> Lo, here am I, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren thou haſt given me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love God's Worſhip, the place of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and thoſe that miniſter about holy things. It was to <hi>Hannah,</hi> praying at <hi>Shiloh;</hi> to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> miniſtring in the Temple; and to the Shunamitiſh woman, that ſo courteouſly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Prophet <hi>Elijah;</hi> and to the Mariner and his Wife, that in Q <hi>Maries</hi> Reign hid that eminent Doctor and Confeſſor, Dr. <hi>Sands,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> to whom God gave Sons, after they had been childleſs a long time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be you your ſelves God's Children, his Sons and his Daughters, and he will give you Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Sons and Daughters, or at leaſt a name bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then of Sons and Daughters, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that fear God, and walk in his way—Thy wife ſhall be as the fruitful vine upon the walls of thine houſe—Thy children like
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45578:29"/>Olive plants round about thy table—Yea, thou ſhalt ſee thy childrens children, and peace upon Iſrael.</hi> And this laſt Clauſe, brings to mind that ſaying of our Saviour, Luke 21.23. <hi>Wo unto them that are with child, and to them that give ſuck in thoſe days.</hi> If you ask why? it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>For there ſhall be great diſtreſs in the land,</hi> namely, of <hi>Iſrael, and wrath upon this people.</hi> Elſe, ſave in caſe of war and deſolation, or in caſe of trouble and perſecution, as the times were like to be when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 1 Cor. c. 7. Elſe, I ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe wombs that bear, and the paps that give ſuck;</hi> the bleſſings of the breaſts and of the womb, are the language of the Holy Tongue: And though in troublous times it is not good, <hi>i.e.</hi> expedient to touch a woman, yet in Serene times, and of <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency, <hi>God ſaid, it is not good for the man to be alone:</hi> And as we have a wo in <hi>Luke</hi> to thoſe that are with child, ſo have we a <hi>Ve ſoli,</hi> a wo to him that is alone, in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes; diſtingue tempora &amp; ſalves difficultatem,</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the times when, or of which theſe things were ſpoken, and you will eaſily reconcile our Saviour's words and his Apoſtles, with thoſe of <hi>Solomon's.</hi> The Hebrew word <hi>Ben,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>a Son,</hi> comes from <hi>Banah,</hi> to build; and thoſe Mothers who bring forth children, are ſaid in Scripture to build up the houſe: So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> prayed for <hi>Boaz</hi> his wife,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45578:30"/>
               <hi>Ruth,</hi> in this manner, <hi>The Lord make the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that is come into thy houſe like Rachel, and like Leah, which two did build up the houſe of Iſrael;</hi> and I may ſay alſo, <hi>Which two did build up the Church of God.</hi> And if they built up God's Church on Earth, they made ready a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple prepared for the Lord in Heaven: And as <hi>Jeruſalem which is above,</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all,</hi> ſo in another reſpect, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is below, I mean the Church on Earth, doth bring forth Sons and Daughters to God, and is the Mother of all the Children of men, that are indeed alſo the Children of God, and Members of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in Heaven, or above.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Education of Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHildren, of themſelves a bleſſing, prove a croſs and a curſe too, unto their Parents, if not cultivated or well managed by a good Education. Teach a Child the way he ſhould go, and he'll not forſake it when he is old: <q>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſervabit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dorem Teſta diu.</q> Although ragged Colts prove often good horſes,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45578:30"/>yet let the horſes run till they are ſix or ſeven years old, wild and unbroken, it will be a hard matter to tame and manage them. 'Tis good that a man bear the yoke in his youth: Blaſpheme not, ſaying, <hi>A young Saint will prove an old Devil;</hi> rather, a <hi>young Devil</hi> is like to prove an <hi>old Beelzebub.</hi> You may bend the <hi>Oak</hi> as well as the <hi>Oſier,</hi> whilſt it is young and tender: Now, now is the time, the ſeaſon, the very nick, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle and joynt of time, when you may turn your Children which way you pleaſe. Oh then, now teach them, mind them to <hi>remember their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the days of their youth;</hi> bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord. Let God have the firſt-fruits of their time, the flower of their age; dedicate them to God betimes, by engaging them to him and his ſervice in the firſt place. God would have Children preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him in the Temple at forty days old, our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God:</hi> And our Lord was pleaſed with the Childrens <hi>Hoſanna's,</hi> as he rode in Triumph to <hi>Jeruſalem: Out of the mouth of babes and ſucklings thou haſt ordained or perfected praiſe,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>God of old call'd to young <hi>Samuel</hi> again and again, whilſt he was a Child, rather than to old <hi>Eli.</hi> We keep a day to Commemorate the young Infants of about two years old, that were
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45578:31"/>murthered for the cauſe of Chriſt, as well as of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> the Protomartyr, and of St. <hi>Paul</hi> the aged, that were put to death for the name of the Lord Jeſus. God of old ſeal'd the males amongſt the Iſraelites at eight days old for his own, his peculiar Treaſure. And if God will own your Children, why do not ye Parents pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to him? Children within the pale of the Church, God looks on as his Children: And if ye take his Children, your Sons and Daughters which you brought unto him, and offer them to <hi>Molock,</hi> to <hi>Baal,</hi> to Idols, or bring them forth, and up, to the Murtherer, or the <hi>Abaddon,</hi> the Deſtroyer of ſouls, by evil or careleſs Education, a thouſand times better had it been they had never been born. How will Children in Hell curſe their Parents, that by their evil counſel, or evil example, or want of good Precepts, and good Paterns, brought them to the place of torment? Oh therefore teach them, by inſtilling good Principles into them betimes, and guide them by your good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; always be able to ſay to them, <hi>Be ye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of us, as we are of Chriſt;</hi> or, <hi>Walk ſo, as ye have us for an example;</hi> drop good and precious inſtructions daily into theſe narrow mouth'd Veſſels, and when they are old, they will retain the good infuſed into them in their young days. Chaſten them if they offend, if you love them, but in meaſure, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45578:31"/>you love them. Correct them, but not in anger, leſt they be diſcouraged, leſt you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to wrath alſo; leſt your bitterneſs to them, imbitter their ſpirits towards you. Teach them Affability, Courteſie, Gentleneſs, Humility, that as you love them, ſo may every body elſe; that ſo they may paſs their time in peace and quietneſs, both at home, in their own boſoms, and abroad in the world.</p>
            <p>Next after they are fitted by a competency of Learning, for ſome honeſt and ſuitable Calling, be ſure you diſpoſe of them accordingly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> hath left on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in one of his Sermons, that <hi>Idle Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and idle Beggars, are the peſts of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth:</hi> Let yours therefore be careful to maintain ſome honeſt Trades or Callings, that they be not unfruitful. <hi>Theſe things are good and profitable unto men.</hi> Whereas the <hi>Grecians</hi> would have all Children to be bound to keep their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents when old, the <hi>Athenians</hi> put in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs their Parents had taught them no Trade whereby to get their living. Every man,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Perkins, beſides his general Calling as a Chriſtian, muſt have ſome perſonal, particular Calling to walk in, either publick or private, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church, or Commonwealth, or Family. Adam</hi> his perſonal Calling aſſigned him by God, was to dreſs and keep the Garden; <hi>and Chriſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45578:32"/>the ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>lived with</hi> Joſeph, ſaith Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, in the calling of a Carpenter:</hi> And hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it was, that the Jews ſaid, <hi>Is not this the Carpenter, the ſon of Mary?</hi> Mark 6.3. Nor is it a calling to devote your Sons and Daughters to be Monks and Nuns in the Monaſteries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas. <hi>The ancient Church,</hi> ſaith the ſame Author, <hi>condemned all Monks for Thieves and Robbers, that beſides the general duties of Prayer and Faſting, did not withal, employ themſelves in ſome other Calling for their better mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give your Children then Callings: If you ask what Callings? I anſwer, 1. according to their Natural inclinations: And ſecondly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Natural parts and gifts. Thoſe Children which excel in the gifts of the body, bring them up to Mechanical Arts; thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which excel in gifts of the mind, bring them up to the Liberal Sciences, to Academical Learning, that they may be ſerviceable thereby in Church or Commonwealth. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> that famous Biſhop, was firſt put to Learning, becauſe he was found by the Sea ſide, doing the part of a Miniſter amongſt a company of little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren like himſelf, examining and baptizing them according to the ſolemn Order uſed in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. The <hi>Athenians,</hi> before they placed their Children in any Calling, did firſt bring them into a Publick Place, where Inſtruments of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45578:32"/>all ſorts were laid; and they obſerv'd, with what kind of Inſtrument they took delight; to the like Art after did they apply them with good ſucceſs. Chriſtians may do well to follow the example of the Heathens in this ſo rational a practice: Chooſe Callings for your Children for which they are fitted, and to which they are inclined; they then will delight in ther Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and their lives will be comfortable to them, their very Callings will be Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>After you have educated your Children, and trained them up in ſome honeſt Calling, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide timely a ſuitable Match for them. 'Tis the Parents duty to diſpoſe of their Children in Marriage; as appears plainly by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.38. <hi>Where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> ſaith my Author, <hi>that the Commandment touching the Marriage of the Child,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Perkins.</hi>
                  </note> is given to the Parent, not the Child.</hi> Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> took a wife for his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſuffer'd himſelf to be diſpoſed of by his Father; afterwards <hi>Iſaac</hi> commanded his ſon <hi>Jacob</hi> to marry in the houſe of <hi>Laban, Gen.</hi> 28. and <hi>Jacob</hi> obeyed. I do not mean, that Parents may abſolutely command their Child to marry this or that perſon, but to marry one thus or thus qualified, according to Rules of Scripture, and right Reaſon and Prudence, I ſay they may. Great is the power of Parents over their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45578:33"/>In ſome Countrys, Parents have power of life and death over their Children. Amongſt the Jews, the Parents might ſell their Children, to free themſelves out of debt; and in caſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were diſobedient and incorrigible, their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents might bring them forth to be ſtoned to death by Gods Law.</p>
            <p>And this brings us to treat of the next Head or Argument <hi>(viz.)</hi> The duty of Children to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards their Parents, <hi>Honour thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſaith the Law; <hi>Which is the firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with promiſe,</hi> ſaith the New Teſtament, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. Parents muſt have a double honour, namely, of Reverence, and of Maintenance; <hi>Thou ſhalt fear thy Mother and thy Father.</hi> And again, according to our Saviour's Interpretation, the Phariſees <hi>Corban non obſtante,</hi> Children were bound to provide for their Parents, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to do or ſhew kindneſs to their Father and Mother; yea, thoſe Chriſtians who do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their own Parents, are worſe than In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels. It is ſad to think of what <hi>Luther</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>That one Father will more willingly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ten Sons, than ten Sons will maintain one Father: but where Children are unnatural to their Parents, God in juſt judgment ſuffers their Children to retaliate their unkindneſs unto themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis memorable, the Story of the Father, who being drawn by his Son to the threſhold of the houſe, by the hair of the head, cryed to him,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45578:33"/>
               <hi>to draw him no further, for that he had drawn his Father no further;</hi> v. <hi>Robinſons Eſſays, p.</hi> 548. 'Tis obſervable, that Children are apt to ſlight their Mother moſt, and her eſpecially in her old age. We are apt to break over the hedge where 'tis loweſt; but the Law of God is a Mound and a Hedge in this Gap, charging us <hi>not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe our Mother when ſhe is old,</hi> Prov. 23.22. And there is a curſe denounced againſt him, that <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth light by father or mother, and all the people were to ſay, Amen to it,</hi> Deut. 27.16. How ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible is that place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.17. <hi>The eye that mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at his father, and deſpiſeth to obey his mother, the Ravens of the Valley ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall eat it.</hi> And he that ſlights his Parents for the infirmities that accompany their old age, or for their wrinkles, or hoary hairs, is very unreaſonable. The natural affection and kindneſs of the Stork to its Dam, may be a witneſs againſt ſuch Children, ſuch worſe than unreaſonable men and women. <hi>Aeneas</hi> is call'd <hi>Pius Aeneus</hi> by the Poet; and why? becauſe he carried his Father <hi>Anchiſes</hi> upon his back, at the deſtruction of <hi>Troy.</hi> We muſt do what we can to hide our Parents nakedneſs: Remember <hi>Chams,</hi> or his ſon <hi>Canaans</hi> curſe, who ſome ſay, firſt ſaw his Grandfather <hi>Noah,</hi> and went and told his Father, and is therefore curſed: We muſt think reverently of them, we muſt ſhew out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reverence to them, bow down to them, or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45578:34"/>riſe up before them; we muſt ſpeak awfully to them, and reſpectively of them: We muſt obey their juſt and lawful commands; if they ſay, Go, we muſt go; if, Come, we muſt come; if, Do this, we muſt do it. We muſt provide neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for them if they want, afford them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we muſt thus honour or reward them for their kindneſs to us. The Jews have a ſaying, <hi>What honour is to be given to Parents?</hi> the anſwer is, <hi>To give them meat and drink, and to cloath them and cover them.</hi> Let's endeavour to procure their hearty prayers for bleſſings to God upon us and ours, and dread the thoughts of their ill Wiſhes, Curſes or Imprecations.</p>
            <p>'Tis memorable what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his <hi>Civ. Dei, b.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. relates, namely, <hi>Often Children, that being curſed by their Mother, went about quaking and trembling from one place to another like Vagabonds.</hi> And I have been very credibly told of a Son, that ſtamping on his Mothers grave, for madneſs becauſe ſhe had given him no more, thereby broke his leg. Though a man muſt love his Wife more than his Mother, yet he muſt reverence his Mother, rather than his Wife. We ſhould honour our Parents living and dead, with Civil honour and reſpect; ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> fell on <hi>Jacob</hi> his Father, and kiſſed him when dead. Give them decent burial; ſo <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> too, buried their Father <hi>Ifaac;</hi> and weep, or mourn, over them. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaking of great
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45578:34"/>ſadneſs, ſaith, he <hi>bowed down heavily, as one th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mourned for his mother,</hi> Pſal. 35.14. and <hi>Joſeph</hi> when he buried his Father, it was with a great and ſolemn mourning, and of a long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.10. If the widows made great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for the death of <hi>Dorcas,</hi> and ſhewed the Coats that ſhe had made for them, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.39. how much more ſhould Children weep and mourn for their deceaſed Parents, from whom under God they had their Beings, their Lives, Education, Food and Cloathing, and Portion and all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CAAP VI. <hi>Of the loſs of Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF God have given you Children, and taken them away again, yet be not like <hi>Rachel, weeping for her children, becauſe they are not;</hi> Rather with <hi>Job</hi> ſay, <hi>The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord,</hi> Job 1.21. Better, I think, to have had Children, though we ſee them go before us to their grave, than to have been always Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; for hereby God hath taken away the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and curſe of Barrenneſs, and hereby you have helped to fill Heaven, and your Children
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45578:35"/>are not loſt, but gone, or ſent thither before you. <hi>Job</hi> who had all his other goods doubled, had not a double number of Children; and this reaſon ſome give of it, becauſe theſe were not loſt, <hi>Job</hi> ſhould meet with them again in Heaven. If your Children dye in the womb, and never ſee the Sun, the Sun in the viſible Heavens, yet may they for ever ſee the Sun of Righteouſneſs in the higheſt Heavens; and ſurely 'tis a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant thing always to behold this Sun, in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and fruition of whom conſiſts ſo much of our happineſs. What though your children dye in the womb, or go out of the world preſently after they are born into it, yet may they ſee God, notwithſtanding the opinion of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that <hi>Duras Infantum Pater;</hi> and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the hard-heartedneſs of the pretended Mother-Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in this a Step-Mother, rather than a true Mother to her Children. The Hebrew Children that dyed before the eighth day; and conſequently before they were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and thoſe Bethlemitiſh Children that were baptized in their own blood; and that child that being born, was alſo baptized and buried in the flames, being thrown into the fire again, the arms of that Midwife that delivered the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred Mother of a live child, doubtleſs were not excluded Heaven for want of a Sacrament, which they did in no wiſe neglect or contemn, but could not have; theſe being comprehended in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45578:35"/>the Covenant made and ſealed to, and with their Parents had a right and title to the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inheritance, were of with God, and co-heirs with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Again conſider, That God may have taken away your Children from the evil to come on the place where they lived. When Storms, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts and Troubles are abroad, you Parents call home your Children, and ſo doth God. God ſaith by his Providence in theſe caſes to his Children, though your Children alſo, <hi>Come my Children, enter into your Chambers, and ſhut the door, till all theſe calamities be overpaſt.</hi> 'Tis a common ſaying, <hi>Quem diligit Dous moritur Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venis,</hi> he whom God loves, dyes young; and ſometime, and in ſome caſes, God calls the ſins of Parents to remembrance, and ſlays their Children. If ſo it be, this is a Lamentation, and ought to be for a lamentation: But upon your Repentance, God may give other Children in room of them he hath taken from you, or himſelf be better than ten Sons, than all Sons and Daughters could be unto you. Learn of <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt of the Lord, who when he had loſt <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> both in one day, and after an extraordinary manner, did not ſay, If it be ſo, why is it thus? but ſaith the Text, <hi>And Aaron held his peace,</hi> Levit. 10.3. he was dumb, and opened not his mouth, becauſe God had done it. <hi>Jonah</hi> was angry becauſe God had
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45578:36"/>ſmitten and withered the Goard, that came up in a night, and periſhed in a night, but <hi>Aaron</hi> acquieſced in Gods handy-work, though he ſlew his two Sons by fire in an extraordinary manner, in all this <hi>Aaron</hi> ſinned not, nor charged God fooliſhly. <hi>Behold, he taketh away, who can hinder him? Who will ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</hi> If thou art either barren, or by the death of thy child childleſs, thou mayeſt do well to educate others Children, you may adopt ſome Kinſman, or Friend, or Neighbours Child, and cultivate them, and ſow the ſeeds of Virtue and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them, and make ſuch your heirs; elſe make the Church, or Poor your heirs, and do not prodigally therefore waſte your Eſtates, or live idly and waſtefully.</p>
            <p>Again, If you have no Child, be humbled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the want of this bleſſing, for Children are ſo, and then encreaſe and abound more in your Devotions towards God; the leſs you are to care for the things of the world, the more reaſon you have, and the more care you ſhould have, how to ſerve and pleaſe God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:45578:36"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Parents that have bad Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF Parents have Children, and they prove croſſes to them, how great is that croſs! If bleſſings, prove curſes; if comforts, turn to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; and your light be darkned in the Heavens thereof, how great is that darkneſs! And yet this may be the caſe of a good man or woman; for Parents are Parents, as men and women, and not as Chriſtians; and Grace and Virtue is not <hi>Ex traducè,</hi> is not propagated. A righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> had a prophane <hi>Cham;</hi> a good <hi>David,</hi> a rebellious Son <hi>Abſolom.</hi> Of ſome Children we may ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is the womb that bare them, and the paps that gave them ſuck!</hi> of others, <hi>It had been good for them, and for their Parents too, if ſuch children had never been born:</hi> 'Tis more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to have none, than wicked Children. It is the Speech and Proteſtation of King <hi>James</hi> in his Preface to his Book to the Prince, <hi>I proteſt before that great God, I had rather not be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Childleſs, than be a Father of wicked Children. I charge you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as ever you think to deſerve my fatherly bleſſing, to follow and put in practiſe, ſo far as lieth in you, the Precepts
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45578:37"/>hereafter following: And if ye follow the contrary courſe, I take the great God to record, that this Book ſhall one day be a witneſs betwixt me and you, and ſhall procure to be ratified in Heaven, the Curſe that in that caſe here I give unto you.</hi> And I find in the life of Reverend Mr. <hi>Robert Bolton,</hi> that he had told his Children ſo much, both in the time of his ſickneſs, and before, he verily believed that none of them durſt think to meet him at that great Tribunal, in an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate eſtate. I confeſs; 'tis a ſad Meditation for a Parent to think of the life or death of a wicked Child. <hi>David,</hi> that was preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted for the death of the young Child he had by <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> refuſed to be comforted for the death of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> ſorely lamenting, <hi>Oh Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, my Son, my Son, I would to God I had dyed for thee, Oh Abſolom, my Son, my Son,</hi> 2 Sam. 18.33. It is thought it was for the manner of his death, the ill condition he dyed in, and for his Soul, that he pierced his heart ſo deeply, and that he wept ſo ſorely. Let good Parents that have bad Children, give them good counſel, and good example, and pray daily with all earneſtneſs, for the return of their Prodigals. St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Mother <hi>Monica,</hi> her Prayers for her Son, when a <hi>Manichee,</hi> were heard at laſt, and he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and became one of the greateſt and beſt Lights of the Church ſince the Apoſtles times. 'Tis thought one cauſe why <hi>Hezekiah</hi> wept ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45578:37"/>ſore at the tidings of death was, becauſe he was then Childleſs; but could the Prophet have told him, that he ſhould have ſuch a Son as <hi>Manaſſeth,</hi> that ſhould commit ſuch abominations, how needs muſt ſuch tidings have made his ears to tingle, and pierce his heart thorough with many ſorrows. Yet this may ſomewhat alleviate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents grief that have bad Children, <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> when he was in Chains, ſought the Lord, and was found of him at the laſt, and that out of his loyns, by his Son <hi>Amon,</hi> came the Mirror of Kings, King <hi>Joſiah.</hi> And if thou haſt matter of ſorrow from thy own immediate Child, thou mayeſt have abundant cauſe of rejoycing from thy Grandchild; thy Childrens Children may praiſe the Lord, and this may be part of thy happineſs, thus to ſee thy Childrens Children, and peace upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And ſith ſo it is, that ſometimes godly Parents have ungodly Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, this ſhould moderate your deſire of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and your grief for the want of them. Let none be ſo impatient or paſſionate as <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſaying to God, or their own Husbands, <hi>Give me Children, or elſe I dye.</hi> It may further be conſidered, that if yet good Parents have divers towardly Children, yet if they have one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> it may break your hearts more than all the reſt can comfort you. Like as in the Natural body, there is more grief by the aking of ſome one part, though but a tooth, than
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45578:38"/>eaſe and comfort in all the reſt that are found and well. And this conſideration, though it ought not to make us judge Children no bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, or not the gift of God, or to be lightly eſteemed; yet may it put us upon being as earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, for to have our Children to be born again, as to be born at firſt; to have them Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by Grace, as ours by nature; and to have his Image and likeneſs on their Souls, as ours on their bodies. When the Parents are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, and endeavour their utmoſt to educate their Children in the fear of God, it uſually follows, that their <hi>labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> The Iſraelites, the holy Scriptures tell us, their Sons and their Daughters, which they had born unto God, they ſacrified unto Devils, Pſal. 106. 37. <hi>Which in a Spiritual ſenſe we do,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>if we either neglect inſtructing them, or praying to God for them; or walking exemplari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as we ought before them. or correcting them duly, or any ſuch means as by which the ſeeds of Grace may grow and proſper in them,</hi> Rob. Eſſ. p. 532, 533.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:45578:38"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Adultery and Fornication,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ALL ſin is accounted filthineſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and compared to the filthieſt things, Scum, Mire, Vomit; but this ſin is <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter,</hi> call'd the fin of Uncleanneſs; 'tis cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo Abomination, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.11. and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.8. Theſe ſins are uſually ſecret ſins, and therefore moſt frequently committed, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſins; <hi>ſtollen waters are ſweet, and bread eaten in ſecret:</hi> and men are prone to forget theſe ſins: the Whore wipes her mouth, and thinks all well. 'Tis obſerved, that the Sacrifice which was offer'd for the woman ſuſpected of Adultery, was call'd an Offering of Memorial, becauſe it was not offer'd to put away ſin, but to bring it to mind, or to remembrance, if it was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Adultery by God's Law, was puniſhed with death, either, as the Rabbins ſay, by ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or they were to be thruſt thorough with a Javelin, as <hi>Phineas</hi> executed <hi>Zimry</hi> or <hi>Cosby;</hi> or they were to be ſtoned with ſtones, if the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel that was defiled was betrothed; ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.23, 24. or elſe by burning with fire, if ſhe that played the Whore was a Prieſts Daughter, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45578:39"/>in her Fathers houſe, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.19. One expounds this, of hot Lead poured into her mouth: This puniſhment was called, <hi>Combuſtio animae;</hi> this puniſhment, they ſay, was uſed in after-times in imitation too of Gods puniſhing with Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereby the outward parts are not hurt, and the inward burnt up, as in the example of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any wonder at what was ſaid before, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the puniſhment of her that was betrothed, in caſe ſhe was defiled or vitiated, that it was greater by God's Law, than of her that was married; <hi>Grotius</hi> gives this Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe ſhe was not in her husbands cuſtody; as ſtealing a ſheep out of the field, was puniſhed more ſeverely, than ſtealing a ſheep out of the fold.</hi> Another Author gives theſe Reaſons, 1. <hi>Becauſe ſhe gave away her Virginity, which her husband moſt eſteemed.</hi> 2. <hi>She brake her promiſe in ſo doing,</hi> Deut. 22.23. 3. <hi>She wrought folly in her Fathers houſe,</hi> Deut. 22.19. 4. <hi>She was not only diſhoneſt to her husband in her firſt love, but diſhonoured alſo her firſt-born (whoſe honour and priviledge amongſt the Jews was very great) and you muſt not ſay her puniſhment ſhould be leſs, becauſe ſhe was not another mans wife, for ſhe is called a neighbours wife,</hi> Deut. 22.24. <hi>and therefore ſhe is ſaid, v.</hi> 22. <hi>to be married to an husband, as if the party were her husband before: If ſo, we know God accounts Idolatry commited by his people Advltery, although
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45578:39"/>the Church is but, as it were, eſpouſed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed to him here, and the wedding and wedding-ſupper to be in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt the Nations, in ſome Countrys, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery was puniſhed by the loſs of both eyes; in ſome by death. Amongſt the Egyptians, by cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the noſe, if he vitiated a free woman. In ſome Country, <hi>illi virilia execantur: The which alſo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Alexander ab Alexandro, was uſed amongſt the Romans.</hi> The ſame Author, <hi>Gen. D. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. tells us, <hi>The Partbians puniſh no crime more grievouſly; that</hi> Opilius Macrinus <hi>condemned ſuch to be burnt with fire; and that amongst the</hi> Arabians <hi>and other Nations, Adultery was always puniſhed capitally: That divers Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers have accounted Adultery a greater crime than Perjury.</hi> In the Chriſtian Church of old, thoſe that admitted ſuch to Communion who had fallen after Baptiſm, excepted thoſe who were guilty of Adultery, Murther and Idolatry. Many and great are the threats againſt ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the holy Scripture; diſgrace and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is threatned to their name, waſting and conſumption to their bodies and eſtates, <hi>a dart ſhall ſtrike through their liver:</hi> Luſt is lodged in the Liver, and there it is eſpecially puniſhed; <hi>Whoremongers and Adulterers,</hi> eſpecially, <hi>God will judge,</hi> Hebr. 13.4. <hi>Neither Fornicators, nor Idolaters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:45578:40"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> our Hiſtoriographer, writing of them any diviſions in <hi>Hungary,</hi> into <hi>Romaniſts, Lutherans, Calviniſts, Yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>all theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent parties do agree in this, to puniſh Adultery and Fornication with no leſs a puniſhment than death; the Father forcing his Daughter, the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band his wife, and the Brother his Siſter to the place of Execution,</hi> H. G. p. 542. King <hi>James</hi> in his <hi>Advice to the Prince,</hi> with much zeal dehorts him from this ſin of Uncleanneſs, <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>&amp;c. Hear God</hi> (ſaith this Engliſh <hi>Solomon,</hi> this King-Preacher) <hi>commanding by the mouth of St.</hi> Paul, <hi>to abſtain from Fornication, declaring that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of Heaven; and by the mouth of St.</hi> John, <hi>reckoning out Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation amongſt other grievous ſins, that debars the Committers, amongst Dogs and Swine, from entry into that ſpiritual and heavenly</hi> Jeruſalem. <hi>And becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſibbeſt examples touches us near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, conſider the difference of ſucceſs that God grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Marriages of the King my Grandfather, and me your own Father; the reward of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency (proceeding from his evil Education) being the ſudden death, at one time, of two plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant young Princes, and a Daughter only born to ſucceed him, whom he had never the hap ſo much as once to ſee or bleſs before his death; leaving a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble curſe behind him to the Land, both a Woman of Sex, and a new born Babe of age to Reign over them. And as for the bleſſing God hath beſtowed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45578:40"/>on me, in granting me both a greater Continency, and the fruits following thereupon, you ſelf and ſib folks to you, are (praiſe be God) ſufficient witneſſes.</hi> And page 81. <hi>Have the King my Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers example before your eyes, who by his Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, bred the wreck of his lawful Daughter and Heir, in begetting that Baſtard, who unnaturally rebelled, and procured the ruine of his own Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign and Siſter.</hi> And this brings to mind, that excellent Captain-General <hi>Gideon,</hi> who had by his Wives Threeſcore and ten Sons, and by his Concubine but one, <hi>viz. Abimelech,</hi> and he ſlew all theſe Threeſcore and ten Sons, except <hi>Joaſh,</hi> who eſcaped his hands, <hi>Judg. chap.</hi> 8 &amp; 9. 'Tis a ſin to beget a Baſtard, and a ſhame to be born one. 'Tis noted on <hi>Job</hi> 31. 10. where <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let my wife grind unto another man, and let others bow down upon her;</hi> the Septuagint render the laſt words, <hi>Let my children be abaſed. Jeptha,</hi> though a valiant, and a gallant, and good man, yet is recorded the baſe Son of <hi>Gilead,</hi> Judg. 11.1. 'Tis a reproach to be thus born, in Scripture-Heraldry; notwithſtanding I have been told, that <hi>William</hi> the Conquerer, King of <hi>England,</hi> did uſe to ſtile himſelf, <hi>Gulielmus Baſtardus Rex Angliae, &amp;c.</hi> God forbad a Baſtard to enter into the Congregation of the Lord, to bear any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, until the tenth Generation, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.3. Yet that ſuch perſons may not be diſcouraged, let them know we have one example, though
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45578:41"/>but one, and that is the example of <hi>Jeptha, a</hi> Judge, and a valiant man, and one eminent for his Faith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.32. ranked amongſt <hi>David, Samuel</hi> and the Prophets. 'Tis a blot to be baſe born, but this may be taken away, in a great meaſure, by good Education. <hi>And then,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>this ſhould be no more a blot unto them, than if they wanted a hand or a leg; and as we blame not the ſtollen ſeed, when it is ſowen and groweth up, but thoſe who ſtole the ſeed, ſo we ſhould not blame the Child begotten out of Marriage (if he follow not his Fathers footſteps) but only his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who begat him. There hath been,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>profitable men in the Church, who have been baſely born, as</hi> Lumbard, Gratian, <hi>and</hi> Petrus Comeſtor, <hi>the Sons of one Whore, and</hi> Darius Nothus <hi>among the Perſian Kings, and</hi> Hercules, <hi>Weem</hi> 3 <hi>Vol. p.</hi> 145. I know the Jews ſtood upon their Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofles, and took it in great dudgion, that our Saviour ſhould tell them, they did not act like the Children of <hi>Abraham;</hi> they retort preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>John</hi> 8.1. <hi>We are not born of fornication.</hi> Yet I ſhould diſſwade from caſting ſuch an ones birth into his diſh, or into his teeth, becauſe never in his power to help it: And I ſhould exhort ſuch who are ſo baſe born, to endeavour to be born again, and then they are truly Noble and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, the Sons of God, and Co-heirs with <hi>Jeptha</hi> the Saint of the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:45578:41"/>
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Second Marriages, and of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of Miniſters or Priests Wives.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OF old they were accounted <hi>Bigamiſts,</hi> or <hi>Digamiſts,</hi> who had two Wives, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at one and the ſame time, but ſucceſſively one after another; and ſuch were enjoyned Penance by the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> and <hi>Neo-Caeſarea;</hi> and by the latter Council, a Presbyter was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to be preſent at the Wedding-feaſt, leſt he ſhould ſeem to conſent to ſuch Marriage; and <hi>Bigamiſts</hi> were not received to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion without prayer and faſting, and repentance firſt enjoyned and exerciſed: And by the ancient Canons, <hi>Bigamiſts</hi> were not to be admitted to holy Orders, <hi>Concil. Andegavenſe, Can.</hi> 11. <hi>Concil. Romanum, an.</hi> 467. <hi>Can.</hi> 2. <hi>Concil. Arelatenſe,</hi> 3. <hi>Decr.</hi> 2. <hi>Concil. Hiſpalenſe</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. and the ſame is forbidden in the Apoſtolical Canons, <hi>Can.</hi> 17. And by the ſame Canons, ſuch as otherwiſe might be capable of being Biſhops, Presbyters and Deacons, are made incapable of being ſuch, if they married a Widow, or a Whore, or one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45578:42"/>that was caſt out by her own Husband, <hi>aut ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam de iis quae publicis ſpectaculis mancipantur, Can.</hi> 18. or one that was a notorious frequenter of the Spectacles in that time.</p>
            <p>By the Law of God, the High Prieſt was not to marry a Widow, or a divorced Woman, or prophane, or an Harlot; <hi>But he ſhall take,</hi> ſaith the holy Text, <hi>a Virgin of his own people to wife, Lev.</hi> 21.14. Another Prieſt was forbidden to take a Wife that was a Whore, or prophane, or any woman put away from her husband, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.7. but was not forbidden to marry a Widow: If the woman was not a Daughter of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or had married to one that it was not lawful for her to marry, or had beeen defiled by conſtraint or unwillingly, or had been ſuſpected of Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by her Husband, though ſhe had not been put to drink the water of Jealouſie, yet by the Law (according to Matrimony) the Prieſt might not lawfully marry with her. The Prieſts of the old Law were not forbidden (except only the High Prieſt, a ſpecial type of Chriſt) to marry a Widow. The High Prieſt was not to marry a Widow, but a Virgin; ('tis thought) that ſo he might have her firſt love; and 2. leſt ſhe ſhould prove with child, and bring in a ſtrange ſeed into the Prieſthood, provided againſt, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.15. Again, he muſt not marry a divorced woman, becauſe it was conjectured ſhe was put away for ſome miſcarriage or miſdemeanor.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45578:42"/>3. He muſt not marry one defiled, either volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily or violently, ſuch a blot muſt not lie on his wife, leſt it ſtain his Function. The Law allows the High Prieſt to marry, but a Virgin; <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>ſhe may be more eaſily guided and ruled, and won to frame her ſelf to duty and obedience.</hi> And in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.22. he was allowed to marry the Widow of a Prieſt; for it may be preſumed, that ſuch an one hath been already trained to Modeſty, to Sobriety, to a chaſte and ſweet Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, beſeeming the wife of a Prieſt. Now although the Miniſters of the New Teſtament are not prohibited, but expreſly allowed to marry; yet muſt their wives be grave, not ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, ſober, faithful in all things, and he that is in holy Orders, muſt be ſure to order and rule his own houſe well, <hi>having his children in ſubjection with all gravity,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.4. &amp; 11. <hi>This care being had, they being married,</hi> ſaith my Author, <hi>ſhall be as holy and honorable in their Function, as the Prieſts of the Old Teſtament, who being married, were ſaid to have the Crown of God upon their heads, and to offer the bread of God, and to be after a ſpecial manner holy.</hi> And where 'tis ſaid, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. &amp; Tit. 1.16. that <hi>a Biſhop muſt be the husband of one wife,</hi> &amp;c. the meaning muſt be, that he muſt not be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to two wives at once, according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Jews, nor have a Concubine, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a lawful wife, accordng to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45578:43"/>of the Gentiles; or he might not marry a ſecond woman, after he had put away the firſt, without any lawful cauſe: But it ſeems to be very improbable, that the Apoſtle ſhould ſeclude from the Calling of a Biſhop or Presbyter, one that married a ſecond wife, after the death of his former. Obſerve, it is not ſaid, that a Biſhop muſt be ſuch a one as hath been the husband of one wife in time paſt; but he uſeth the preſent time, both in <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> The High Prieſt himſelf under the Law, might have a wife af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his firſt wife, if ſhe was dead; if he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a maid, which was a figure of Chriſts Spouſe, the Church, which was to be preſented holy, and as a chaſte Virgin to Chriſt: By the ſame reaſon that they may drive Miniſters from their wives, they may alſo deprive them of all uſe of wine; and they may deprive Miniſters of all uſe of meat, and command them to faſt always, that they may be fit to pray always, as well as alway to abſtain from their wives: We never read, that the Levites that taught in the Synagogues (into the place of which our Churches ſucceed) were barred from the company of their wives. And conſider, it may be as neceſſary to marry the ſecond time, as the firſt, and ſometime, and in ſome caſes, perhaps more neceſſary [ſays Dr. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi>] The wife may dye preſently after Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and without Children, and the ſecond Marriage in that caſe tending as much to the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45578:43"/>ends of Matrimony (Comfort of life, Propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, remedy of Luſt) as the former can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to do; it would then be ſtrange to debar a Biſhop or Presbyter in ſuch a condition. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> with divers others, plainly and clearly teach this place to be underſtood as we do, that a Biſhop ſhould not have two wives at once. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> upon the place, diſliked the then practice of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Marriage to Biſhops and Prieſts: <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>inceſtus, admittitur homicida, admittitur pirata, admittitur Sodomita, ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus parricida, deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quis non? ſolus digamus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluditur ab hoc honore, qui ſolus nihil admiſit:</hi> And further, conſidering the times, and the ill conſequence of the ſingle life amongſt their Clergy and Monks, he inclines to think they had better much to allow Matrimony to theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: <hi>Nunc caelibes habet Mundus quamplurimos, caſtos perpaucos. Grotius</hi> ſaith, <hi>I confeſs, that amongst all Nations, ſecond Marriages were leſs honoured, and amongst ſome, theſe were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by puniſhments.</hi> And that <hi>Tertullian</hi> is fierce againſt ſecond Marriages, condemning them as unlawful, and interprets this of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, againſt a Biſhops being twice married. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which Authorities, let the Scripture and right Reaſon be heard, and what hath been premiſed on this Argument conſidered, and you will have good ground and cauſe, not to call
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45578:44"/>good, evil; I meann not to condem ſecond Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, whether in Lay-men or Clergy. And if a Biſhop may, without ſin, marry a ſecond wife, after he has buried his former, ſurely then he may lawfully marry at firſt: If he cannot contain, let him marry, he ſinneth not, only let him <hi>marry in the Lord,</hi> an honeſt, grave, ſober perſon, that may adorn, and not blemiſh his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Function.</p>
            <p>The Romaniſts ſay, <hi>there are three ſpecial Crowns reſerved in Heaven; one for Martyrs, a ſecond for Virgins, and a third for Doctors: The Virgins, overcome the fleſh; the Martyrs, overcome the World; and the Doctors, overcome the Devil.</hi> They have no ſuch Crown for married perſons; but although they have none for them, God hath laid up for them a Crown of Righteouſneſs, even the like Crown of Righteouſneſs for every one that loves the appearing of Chriſt, the Judge of quick and dead, as that Virgin Apoſtle, as moſt ſay, the Doctor of the Gentiles, and eminent Martyr, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.7, 8. <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>is not a Virtue in it ſelf, and no more acceptable to God than Marriage is;</hi> and this he proves, <hi>Becauſe all Virtues by Repentance may be reſtored: But Virginity cannot be reſtored, and therefore it is not a Virtue.</hi> Again, <hi>Becauſe all Virtues in time and place are commanded: But Virginity is left free, and only</hi> Paul <hi>gives his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to it,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. <hi>therefore it is not a Virtue.</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:45578:44"/>The ſame Author ſaith, <hi>That Virginity is not good in it ſelf, but good for another end; when a man having the gift of Continency, lives a ſingle life, that he may be more fit or free to ſerve God.</hi> The Papiſts gloſſing on the Parable of the Sower, ſay, <hi>That Virginity bringeth forth an hundred-fold; Widowhood, ſeventy fold; and Marriage, but thirty-fold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great is the difference 'twixt the Ancient Church of God amongſt the Jews, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this matter; there in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 78.63. <hi>The Virgins were not given in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage;</hi> or, <hi>were not praiſed,</hi> ſo the Hebrew ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies: But in this Church, the Virgins which are not married are moſt praiſed. Celibacy is made here a ſtate of Perfection, or Supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Meritorious; but if but one half be true which we find in our Chronicles, it had been happy for our Votaries, very many of them at leaſt, that they had never known their Cells and Cloyſters; they might have gone as near a way to Heaven out of the World, as out of their Monaſteries. <hi>Bale,</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Acts of the Roman Biſhops,</hi> ſaith. <hi>That when the Kings Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors in</hi> England, <hi>in the year,</hi> 1538. <hi>viſited the Abbies, they found in ſome of their Styes, rather than Religious Houſes, five, in ſome ten, in ſome twenty Sodomites and Adulterers; of which ſome kept five, ſome ſeven, ſome twenty Harlots.</hi> And a later Hiſtorian tells us, <hi>That</hi> Barkley <hi>Nuns were
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45578:45"/>all with child at once, and how Sir</hi> Henry Colt <hi>cauſed a Buckstal to be ſet in the narroweſt place of the Marſh, from</hi> Cheſhnut <hi>Nunnery to</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham <hi>Abby, and therein took the Monks of</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham <hi>as they paſſed homewards in the night; and the next morning he brought and preſented them to the King, namely, to King</hi> Hen. 8. <hi>who had often ſeen ſweeter, but never fatter Veniſon;</hi> D.F.H. <hi>6 b. p.</hi> 317. And 'tis reported that Dr. <hi>Smith,</hi> who diſputed at <hi>Oxford</hi> againſt <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and who had written a Book for the Celibacy of Prieſts, was taken himſelf at <hi>Oxford</hi> in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or in the very act. This is enough to prove, That 'tis much eaſier to make an Eloquent Speech, or write a Learned Book in Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Single-life, and of Chaſtity in that condition, than to live ſo. If you Object the practice and praiſe of the Monks of Antient times: I anſwer, That the Monks of old times, and our preſent Votaries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are very different.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They lived ſingle, without any Vow of Continency, theſe are Votaries.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They had Callings, and got their bread in the ſweat of their brows; theſe live idle moſt of them, and like Drones, conſume the honey which others have gathered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They did not look upon that condition, as a ſtate of greater perfection, and in it ſelf Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious; theſe do.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:45578:45"/>
            <p n="4">4. Some of them, as I take it, had wives; and theſe not, but eſteem it more lawful to have a Concubine than a Wife.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Monks were none of the Popes licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or founding; theſe are. We read of 12000 Monks of <hi>Bangor,</hi> that were deſtroyed by the King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> for not ſtooping to <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk, upon the inſtigation as (Hiſtory tells us) of <hi>Auſtin.</hi> The Original of Monkery, or the Pattern or Platform of it, is not taken in the Mount; <hi>viz.</hi> in or from the holy Scriptures; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though perhaps, ſome would pretend that they imitate <hi>Jeptha</hi>'s Daughter, or <hi>Elijab,</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus,</hi> or the Nazarites, or St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> or the Children of <hi>Jonadab</hi> the Son of <hi>Rechab. But who hath required theſe things at their hands,</hi> now under the Goſpel, to tread in the ſteps of thoſe before-mentioned? and yet <hi>Jeptha</hi>'s Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bewailed her Virginity, and ſo 'tis thought did yearly the Daughters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> lament on her account, or for her ſake. As for our Nazarites, they might marry, and ſome were married, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> and <hi>Samuel.</hi> Again, the Monks and Anchorites of old, were neceſſitated to that Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary life; theſe live ſo out of choice, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily obliging themſelves to this courſe. <hi>Elijah, Eliſha,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, were all extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Perſons and Prophets, had extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Calls, and are not to be imitated by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Chriſtians. It is noted by Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:45578:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>that <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith, <hi>in the life of</hi> Hilarion, <hi>that there was no Monk in</hi> Syria,
<note place="margin">See his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Problem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Hilarion, <hi>who was the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that Profeſſion in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</hi> And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in the 25 <hi>Hom. ad Hebraeos,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That in</hi> Pauls <hi>time there was no ſign nor ſtep of any Monk.</hi> Monaſtical Profeſſion began in the Church about 260 years after our Redemption, by <hi>Paul</hi> a <hi>Thebane; or rather,</hi> ſaith my Author, <hi>about the three hundredth year by</hi> Antony. Theſe Monks, or Hermites, lived alone in Fields or Deſarts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil,</hi> 'tis ſaid, firſt invented Monaſteries, and was head of the Monks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil,</hi> himſelf, <hi>Ep.</hi> 65. ſaith, <hi>That the</hi> Neo-Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians <hi>objected the Novelty of Monaſtical life againſt him.</hi> Beſides, theſe Monks of old were Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and not Clergy-men; and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Dracontius,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he knew many, both Monks and Biſhops that were married, and had Children. There were no Nuns,</hi> ſaith <hi>Mr.</hi> Perkins, <hi>until about two hundred years after Chriſt, and theſe lived continent and freely, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, out of Monaſteries.</hi> In <hi>Rome, Marcella</hi> was one of the Nuns, about the year 400. <hi>vid. Hieron. in Epitap. Marcellae.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> doth not approve of the idle lives of Monks. <hi>The Solitary life,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>is inferior to the common and ordinary life, becauſe it is full of importunate co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neither do we ſpeak this out of bare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45578:46"/>conjecture, but have learned it of thoſe who have tried it, to be true.</hi> Ivo Carnotenſis. Ep 258.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now give ſome Anſwer to the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the married lives of the Clergy, or of men in holy Orders, taken from the Scriptures. The Scriptures that have been, are, or may moſt ſeemingly be alledged to the contrary are theſe, <hi>Thoſe that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,</hi> Rom. 8.8. <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.16. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud not one another, except it be by conſent, for a ſeaſon, that ye may give your ſelves to prayer and faſting,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.5. <hi>'Tis good for a man not to touch a woman,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.1. <hi>He that is unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, careth how to pleaſe the Lord; but he that is married, careth how to pleaſe his wife,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.33. <hi>No man that is choſen to be a Souldier, intangleth himſelf with the affairs of this life,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.4. <hi>Whoſoever hath left Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Houſe, or Land, for my ſake, or the Goſpels, ſhall receive a hundred-fold in this life,</hi> Mat. 19.29. <hi>There are that make themſelves Eunuchs for the Kingdom of Heaven; he that can receive it, let him receive it,</hi> Mat. 19.12. <hi>Younger widows re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; for when they wax wanton againſt Chriſt, they will marry, having damnation, becauſe they have forſaken their firſt faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.11, 12. <hi>The unmarried woman careth for the things of the Lord, that ſhe may be holy both in body and ſpirit; but ſhe that is married, careth for the things of this world, how ſhe may pleaſe her husband,</hi> 1 Cor.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45578:47"/>7.34. To theſe Objections from Scripture, I anſwer in general;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Scripture directly and plainly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Marriage to Miniſters, equally as to any ſort of men, 1. Saying, <hi>That Marriage is honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able among all men</hi> (and therefore amongſt Clergy-men) <hi>and the bed undefiled,</hi> Hebr. 13.4.2. And again, <hi>Let every man have his own wife,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.2. and if every man, then a Prieſt, or Presbyter may lawfully have a wife. 3. <hi>A Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop must be the husband of one wife; and one that hath his children in ſubjection, with all gravity,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſay, That the High Prieſt and Prieſts of the old Law, had liberty to marry; that <hi>Aaron</hi> the Saint of the Lord was married, and had Children; <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> &amp;c. that divers of the Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally married; that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe Succeſſor the Pope, or Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> claims to be, was married, our Saviour healing S. <hi>Peters</hi> wives Mother of a Feaver, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.14, 15. Nor doth it any where appear, that they did wholly forſake ſociety with their Wives, any more than their Houſes, Trades, Ships, to which they certainly ſometime after, at leaſt for a time, returned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Scotus, Aquinas, Bellarmine, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus à Sancta Clara,</hi> divers in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and of the Romiſh Church, hold, that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45578:47"/>the Celibacy, or ſingle life of Prieſts, is not <hi>de Jure Divino;</hi> and therefore cannot be proved out of Scripture, either by Precept, Inſtitution, or Example.</p>
            <p>To the particular Scriptures, beſides what hath been ſaid before to ſeveral of them, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Thoſe that are in the fleſh, cannot pleaſe God;</hi> muſt not be interpreted or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, thoſe that are in Wedlock cannot pleaſe God; becauſe we know, that many Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, were married, and yet pleaſed God; and <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, and God took him up to Heaven, that he ſaw not death; for before he was tranſlated, he had this Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>that he pleaſed God,</hi> Heb. 11.5. But by thoſe <hi>that are in the fleſh,</hi> muſt be meant, either thoſe that adhere to the old Law, and ſlight the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; or elſe thoſe that are in a ſtate of Nature, in an unregenerate eſtate, never as yet renewed in the Spirit of their minds, but ſtill remain car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded, and drowned in the corruptions and ſinful luſts of the fleſh. To that of <hi>Peter, Be ye holy, for I am holy;</hi> it concerns all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and if Marriage and Holineſs could not conſiſt together, neither Lay-men nor Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould marry; and again, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and God's people of old, to whom theſe words were ſpoken, were married perſons, and not commanded thereby to put away their wives. To the third, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Defraud not one another,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45578:48"/>&amp;c.</hi> that it is ſaid to all indifferently Lay-men, as well as Clergy-men, and that it forbids to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the man from the ſociety of the woman, or his wife, wholly and perpetually, but only for a time, and that too, that they might give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to faſting and prayer, and ſo come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again; and this too, was to be done by the mutual conſent of man and wife.</p>
            <p>Here may be condemned then, the Romaniſts barring perſons in holy Orders from Marriage, or in caſe they have been married before, from Conjugal fellowſhip with their wives whilſt they live, and that whether the wife will or no. We never read, that the Apoſtles ſo left their wives, nor that ever they asked their conſent ſo to do; and their ſaying, that the Apoſtles, although they were married, yet after they were called to the Apoſtleſhip, never did accompany with their wives any more, is <hi>gratis dictum,</hi> a meer ſay-ſo, a fancy of their own brain, without any good ground or foundation from Scripture, or ſound Reaſon, or good Authority. To the fourth Scripture, <hi>viz. That 'tis good for a man not to touch a woman.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>Good</hi> there, is taken for expedient, and that by reaſon of the preſent diſtreſs, and the danger of perſecution; in a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſtate or condition in ſuch times, they ſhould meet with troubles. To the fifth, <hi>viz.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>I ſay, that Souldiers do not uſe, whilſt they are engaged in Military imployment, to undertake
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45578:48"/>and intangle themſelves with merchandize or hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry,</hi> &amp;c. But this notwithſtanding, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did work with his hands to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf, that he might not be charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> becauſe of falſe Teachers, who would have taken advantage, if he had been chargeable to that Church. And nevertheleſs, the Romaniſts do allow perſons in holy Orders, to be Juſtices of the peace, Lord Chancellors, Ambaſſadors of Princes: And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did allow of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> his having a wife; and I have been told, that Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks wives take on them, and off from their husbands, the cares of the Houſhold and Family: ſo that by Marriage, they are freed from worldly cares, rather than immerſt in them.</p>
            <p>The caſe is not now with Clergy-men, as in the Apoſtles days; then the Church was poor and deſtitute, now ſhe is rich, and her Officers are well provided with Houſes, Glebe and Tythes, and neceſſaries for Houſe-keeping and Hoſpitality; and now a Houſe-keeper, eſpecially in times of peace, may be as expedient, as it was inexpedient in the Apoſtles time, and days of perſecution. To the ſixth, <hi>viz.</hi> Mat. 19.29. I anſwer, That if the times be ſo, that a man cannot be a good Chriſtian, or follower of Chriſt, except he leave or forſake his wife, houſe, lands, &amp;c. then he muſt leave all, or deny all theſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45578:49"/>things and relations, rather than deny Chriſt; and that this concerns the Laity, as well as the Clergy. If our Saviour had ever taught any ſuch Doctrine, as to part man and wife for the ſake of his Religion, and as part of his Religion, how would the Scribes and Phariſees have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied unto him from his own mouth, <hi>That which God hath joyned together, let not man put aſunder.</hi> Beſides, it no where appears, that the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did wholly and perpetually forſake the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of their wives; but rather, when they were to fly, took them with them, in caſe they would accompany them in their travels. To the ſeventh Scripture, I ſay, He that hath the gift of Continency may, if he ſees that Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age will prove a ſnare to him, and intangle him ſo in the cares of the world, that he ſhall not be free and able to ſerve God as he ought: I ſay, let not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> marry; but this is far from proving, that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in holy Orders, whether they have the gift or not, ſhould vow Continency, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Marriage, in caſe of a mans not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to contain. The bleſſed Apoſtle, who knew the mind of his and our Lord, hath left us a general Rule, <hi>Notwithſtanding to avoid For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, let every man have his own wife,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.2. To the eighth Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 Tim. 5.11, 12. I anſwer, That as therefore becauſe younger widows were likely (after they had made promiſes to live to their lives end (as Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conneſſes,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45578:49"/>to miniſter to the Church; in attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſick and weak) to change their minds, and marry perhaps to Infidel husbands, and ſo be in danger of forſaking their Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and prove a great ſcandal to Chriſtianity, making it be ill thought of by the world; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would not by any means have theſe younger widows admitted into ſuch Offices, but only ſuch widows as were above threeſcore years old, and ſo out of the danger of deſires of marriage, or altering their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So I could heartily wiſh, that no vow of Single life or Continency, might be put upon young perſons of either Sex, upon pretence of admitting them to any Office, or of ſeparating them to any ſpecial devotion, leſt they be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to break ſuch their Vows. This is the right and beſt uſe we can make of this Teſtimony. To the ninth Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.34. I ſay, that it doth not condemn Marriage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or unholineſs; but it imports and implies, that ſingle perſons, taken off from the care and ſollicitude about the world, may more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly ſerve God; and having the gift of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, they may purely ſerve God with body and ſoul, not being overcome with any tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Fornication or Uncleanneſs: Not but that he or ſhe that is married, may and ought to be, and oft-times are pure, chaſte and holy both in body and ſoul. <hi>Marriage is honourable
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45578:50"/>amongst all, and the bed undefiled;</hi> and the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried as well as unmarried, may keep their veſſel in Sanctification and honour, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.4. To that about <hi>Carefulneſs,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, That if God call his ſervants to a married condition, he can and will, if ſought unto, give Grace to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe lets, and bear theſe perſecutions they meet withal, ſo, as they may turn to helps and furtherances in the Kingdom of God, and to a richer Crown of Glory in the ſame, than the Virgins come unto; which becauſe they never wreſtled with ſuch mighty temptations, cannot wear the like Crown of Victory that they do, <hi>v. T. C. in loc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt place of Scripture that is alledged, is Rev. 14.4. <hi>Theſe are they which are not defiled with women, for they are Virgins; theſe are they which follow the Lamb, whitherſoever he goeth; theſe were redeemed from amongst men, being the firſt fruits unto God, and to the Lamb.</hi> By <hi>Virgins,</hi> we are to underſtand all thoſe pure Chriſtians, who had kept themſelves pure from the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> Corruptions and Uncleanneſs, or from Idolatry, which is Spiritual Fornication; and have loyally adhered to Chriſt, the only Bridegroom of the Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. By thoſe that are ſaid <hi>not to be defiled with women,</hi> we muſt not underſtand thoſe that are not married, as if they that were in that ſtate were defiled with women; the Scripture reaches the contrary, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. The
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45578:50"/>Marriage-bed, is <hi>the bed undefiled;</hi> and Chriſt is followed whereſoever he goeth, not only by the bleſſed Saints that have led a ſingle life, and were not married; but alſo by married perſons, as Patriarchs, Apoſtles, Martyrs, and innumerable others, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. 'Tis obſerved, that there is nothing ſaid of theſe Virgins, which agreeth not to all the faithful. 1. They have all the name of the Lamb, his Father, and written in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads; and all God's ſervants are ſealed in their foreheads, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.3. 2. All God's ſervants are to ſing the new Song, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, 10. all are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the earth, by the blood of the Lamb, <hi>chap.</hi> 5.9. The believing Jews, they are all a kind of firſt-fruits unto God, <hi>James</hi> 1.18. Laſtly, The Jeſuites at <hi>Rhemes</hi> confeſs, that theſe are the ſame number of the Elect that were ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. where in the Margent they note, That by the number there ſpoken of, are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood all the Elect, both of the Jews, and of the Gentiles, <hi>vid. T. C. in loc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Virgins then are thoſe, that would not be polluted or defiled with the Idolatry, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Fornication of the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Verſe</hi> 8. of the 14 <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Revelations.</hi> Whatever Papiſts or old Hereticks ſay againſt the lawful Conjugal ſociety of man and wife, as if it were a work of the fleſh; the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth not rank or condemn it for a work of the fleſh, in that black Catalogue
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45578:51"/>of the works of the fleſh, on Record, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. But on the other ſide 'tis obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that thoſe who decry Marriage, without a juſt cauſe, and cry up ſingle life more than they have cauſe, as the Papiſts do, they are verily guilty of Idolatry, which is Spiritual Adultery or Fornication; witneſs their worſhip of the Croſs with Religious worſhip; their worſhip of Images, of Saints, and particularly of the B. Virgin; their worſhip of Angels, with Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, with Adoration. They tell us a ſtory, that at the Synod held at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> when there was a difference 'twixt the married Clergy and the Monks, and Archbiſhop <hi>Dunſtan</hi> had a mind to introduce the Monks, <hi>The Croſs ſpake</hi> humano more, <hi>with mans voyce, againſt the married Prieſts.</hi> This was in the days of King <hi>Edgar,</hi> who began his Reign, 959. It ſeems then that there were married Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> in thoſe days.</p>
            <p>If it be Objected, That many Ancient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils have ordained <hi>Celibacy</hi> for Prieſts, as the firſt <hi>Elibertine</hi> Council, <hi>an.</hi> 310. or 311. <hi>Can.</hi> 33. The ſecond Council of <hi>Cartharge,</hi> about the year <hi>396. Can.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concilium Agathenſe, Can.</hi> 9. about the year, 506.</p>
            <p>The third Council of <hi>Orleans,</hi> Can. 1. about the year 537. The fourth Council of <hi>Orleans, an.</hi> 547. <hi>Can.</hi> 17. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>My Anſwer is, That we have the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45578:51"/>of the Old and New Teſtament, for the lawfulneſs of Prieſts or Presbyters marriage, the Canons of the Apoſtles, <hi>Can.</hi> 5. and the General Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> rejecting the Propoſal about prohibiting of it; as alſo the ſixth General Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> &amp;c. in the year, 692. and the Council of <hi>Toledo,</hi> an. 400. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. &amp; 7. which teſtifies that the Clergy had wives. I might alſo have alledged <hi>Concilium Gangrenſe, cap.</hi> 4. in or about the year, 324. which Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematiſeth thoſe who held it unlawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the bleſſed Sacrament at the hands of a married Prieſt; and many Councils which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Prieſts ſecond Marriage, or to marry a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which ſuppoſed it lawful for him to marry. Whatever the Canons decreed, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that the <hi>Greek</hi> Church unto this day, allow of a married Clergy; and that divers Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Countreys, for a long time in the Weſt, did not admit of this neceſſary Celibacy, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated their Clergy to be married. In <hi>England</hi> they had their wives, for above a thouſand years, almoſt twelve hundred years after Chriſt. So in <hi>Ireland,</hi> till the days of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of <hi>England,</hi> who began his Reign, 1155.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Pius</hi> II. who ſate about the year, 1458. was a great man in the Council of <hi>Baſil,</hi> his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was, <hi>That Marriage was better for the Clergy than ſingle life, and turned out divers cloyſtered Nuns to take their liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:45578:52"/>
            <p>
               <hi>De facto</hi> many Prieſts were married of old. So <hi>Novatus</hi> a Prieſt, permitted by <hi>Cyprian</hi> to live with his wife. <hi>Tertullian</hi> was married, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by his Book written to his wife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gratian</hi> tells of the Sons of Presbyters and Biſhops, that were promoted to the Papal Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Diſt.</hi> 56. So was <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the Pope, the Son of <hi>Jucundus</hi> the Presbyter; <hi>Foelix</hi> the Pope, the Son of <hi>Foelix</hi> the Presbyter; <hi>Agapetus</hi> the Pope, Son of <hi>Gordianus</hi> the Presbyter; <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the Pope, Son of <hi>Theodorus</hi> the Biſhop; <hi>and many more,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>there were;</hi> and addeth, <hi>we are not to underſtand them as born out of lawful Marriages, which were lawful to Prieſts, before the Prohibition,</hi> ibid. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> agreeth with <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and ſaith, <hi>That Marriage is in ſo high a degree honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that men with it may aſcend into the Epiſcopal Chairs, and yet live with their wives.</hi> For though it be a hard thing, yet it is poſſible ſo to perform the duties of Marriage, as not to be wanting in the performance of the duties of a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſaith of <hi>Spiridion, that though he had a Wife and Children, yet he was not therefore any whit the more negligent in performing the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Calling;</hi> and of <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> it is reported, <hi>that though he was married, he was no way inferior to his worthy Brother, that lived ſingle:</hi> And howſoever in <hi>Theſſaly; Theſſalonica, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> they did not admit into the Miniſtry any
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45578:52"/>ſingle perſons, yet all the Biſhops of the Eaſt beſides, were then left unto their own liberty; and though ſome went about to take away their liberty in ſome places, yet the worthieſt men the Church had, ſtood in defence of it. So <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſius,</hi> when they of <hi>Ptolemais</hi> would needs have him to be their Biſhop (which thing he little deſired) he made them acquainted with his preſent condition, and reſolved purpoſe for the time to come: <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Law, and the ſacred hand of</hi> Theophilus, <hi>have given to me a wife, I therefore tell all men aforehand, and teſtifie unto all, that I will neither ſuffer my ſelf to be altogether eſtranged and ſeparated from her, neither will I live with her ſecretly as an Adulterer; for the one of theſe is no way pious and godly, and the other no way lawful: But I will deſire and pray unto God, that exceeding many and moſt good and happy Children may be born unto me: Neither will I have him that is chief in ordaining of me, to be ignorant hereof.</hi> Syneſius ad fratrem Ep. 105. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This liberty the Council in <hi>Trullo</hi> impeached in reſpect of Biſhops, but in reſpect of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45578:53"/>it continueth in all the Eaſt Churches of the world unto this day, <hi>Greek, Armenian</hi> and <hi>Ethiopian;</hi> warranted unto them by the Canons of the Apoſtles judgement of Biſhops, Canons of councils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dr. <hi>Field of the Ch. l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 708. Some attempts were made in the Eaſt, by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sebaſtia;</hi> in <hi>Armenia</hi> and in the Weſt by <hi>Siricius,</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt his Succeſſor; and ſome Canons were made in the ſecond, or rather laſt Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> to the contrary. Yet by degrees theſe Canons and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities againſt the married Clergy lay dormant, being found a burthen too heavy for the Church to bear. We find, that in the time that <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand</hi> climb'd up into the Papal Chair, namely, <hi>anno</hi> 1075. and long before, that Prieſts had wives publickly: This was he, that was neither choſen by Emperor or Clergy, but intruded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; this was he, that threw the Sacrament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire; this was he, that forced the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, whom he had Excommunicated, to come with his Empreſs and Son bare footed, in the cold of Winter, to his Caſtle at <hi>Canuſium,</hi> and there to wait three days faſting, until he might have audience; which at length was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the mediation of Madam <hi>Matilda</hi> the Popes Minion, that left her husband to live with the Pope, <hi>vid. Plat.</hi> this was he, that Sainted his Predeceſſor <hi>Liberius</hi> the <hi>Arrian;</hi> and this was he, that reſtrained and forbad Prieſts Marriage;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45578:53"/>but by ſo doing, ſtirred up the whole Nation of Clergy-men againſt him, crying out, that he was an Heretick, and a man damnably erring in his judgement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And it is ſo far from being true, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Prieſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to marry in</hi> Gregories <hi>days, was the cauſe of the great contempt of the Sacrament, and of the Confuſions and Prophanations of Sacred things in thoſe days,</hi> that it was clear contrary; as <hi>Nauclerus</hi> teſtifies, <hi>de Clericis, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>that it was an old and confirmed cuſtom, that was not eaſily to be altered; and the Prieſts rather in</hi> Gregories <hi>time ceaſed, than began to marry, by reaſon of the attempts and endeavours of</hi> Gregory <hi>to reſtrain them from marriage; and the cauſes of the Confuſions of thoſe times, were occaſioned ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the forbidding the Prieſts to marry, than by their beginning then to marry.</hi> And now ſince the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath forced this ſingle life on Clergy men, very many Learned men of later times, have deſired the Law of ſingle life may be taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Durandus</hi> in his Book <hi>de Modo celebrandi Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii,</hi> proveth by many Reaſons, that it were fit that the liberty of Marriages were again reſtored to Prieſts, in a General Council. <hi>Aeneas Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius,</hi> after Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond, was of this mind, So was <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus;</hi> the firſt of theſe in <hi>Book</hi> 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>de Invent. rerum,</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>I dare confidently ſay, that it hath been
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45578:54"/>ſo far from being true, that this inforced chaſtity hath excell'd that which is in Marriage: That no ſinful crime hath brought greater diſgrace to the Order of the Miniſtry, more evil to Religion, or made a greater and deeper impreſſion of ſorrow in all good men, than the ſtain of the impure luſts of Prieſts. Eraſmus</hi> in <hi>Declam. de laudibus Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monii,</hi> affirms, <hi>that in his conceit, he ſhould not ill deſerve, nor take the worſt courſe, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of humane affairs, and the right informing of the manners of men, which ſhould procure li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Marriage (if it might be) both for Prieſts and Monks:</hi> Read alſo his Annotations on the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> chap. 3.1. And <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> the Emperor, a little before the Council of <hi>Baſil,</hi> declar'd and publiſhed, <hi>That foraſmuch as more evil cometh by the forbidding of Marriage than good, it were better and more ſafe to permit Clergy men to live in the ſtate of Marriage, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of the Oriental Churches, than to forbid them ſo to live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antiochus</hi> aforementioned, a Figure of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.37. did not regard women, or the deſire of women, or of wiving; and the Antichriſt forbids to marry, and commands to abſtain from meats. The ancient Romans liked and encouraged Marriage. Thus the Figure and Forerunner of Antichriſt, he himſelf and his followers, decry wiving, and cry up ſingle life; and by Fryers and Monks, the great Adorers of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45578:54"/>ſingle life, and Obſervers of diſtinctions of meats, the Doctrine of Image-worſhip was brought and ſpread, and propagated in the Church; as is proved by Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> in his <hi>Apoſtacy of the latter times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of theſe Hermites, Anchorites, or Monks and Coenobites, might be honeſt and good per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, abating them their errour about over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magnifying the ſingle life; yet the generality of them he condemns as hypocrites: For the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Marriage of perſons in holy Orders, we have the Old and New Teſtament, and the practice of the Church, and the Doctrine of the Church at the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> and after, till the time of <hi>Siricius,</hi> about the year, 385. Afterwards we have the Marriage of theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all thoſe Councils which forbid ſuch perſons to marry widows, ſuch as <hi>Concilium Epaunen.</hi> Canon 2. <hi>Aurelianum</hi> the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, <hi>Can.</hi> 15. <hi>Concilium Toletanum</hi> 1.&amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 1. the 3. And we find the Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> made di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Canons, about the Government of the Sons and Daughters of Biſhops and Clergy-men, ſuch as the 11. <hi>That they ſhould not make or go to the</hi> Spectacula Secularia, <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>That their Sons and Daughters ſhould not marry to Heathens, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks or Schiſmaticks,</hi> c. 14. <hi>That they ſuffer not their Sons to go free out of their power and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, till they are aſſured of their manners, and of ſuch age,</hi> ut poſſint ad eos propria perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45578:55"/>peccata. This Council was held, ſaith <hi>Coriolanus,</hi> 397. The firſt Council of <hi>Toledo,</hi> an. 400. c. 1. Ordains <hi>de Presbyteris &amp; Deaclnis, ſi poſt ordinationem filios genuerint, ad altiorem gradum non aſcendant.</hi> Yet they might continue in their ſtation, though not riſe higher in the Church.</p>
            <p>In the year, 506. <hi>Conſilium Agathenſe,</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>Symmachus,</hi> cap. 1. although Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamiſts, and thoſe that had married widows, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Presbyters or Deacons, might not conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate or miniſter; yet they might retain the name of Presbyters and Deacons. Hence it is to be ſuppoſed, that Presbyters and Deacons, who were not Bigamiſts, nor had married widows, might conſecrate and miniſter, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their marriage.</p>
            <p>If it be Objected, That there were endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make the Clergy content themſelves without wives. I ſay, yet in many places it would not prevail; not in <hi>England,</hi> till above Eleven hundred years after Chriſt; not in <hi>Ireland,</hi> till the days of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second of <hi>England,</hi> who ſubdued <hi>Ireland.</hi> I read, that <hi>Celſus</hi> the great Apoſtle of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and High Primate of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> had both a wife and children, in the time of his Archbiſhopry, according to the uſage of the Countrey, <hi>vid. Bernard</hi> in <hi>vita Malachiae.</hi> And we are told, that Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> and Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> did ſtir up <hi>Henry</hi> the Second to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45578:55"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> becauſe the people withſtood their proceedings againſt the Marriage of Biſhops and Prieſts.</p>
            <p>It is certain <hi>de facto,</hi> that many Eminent Perſons, in holy Orders, were actually marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: So <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>'s Father was a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and begat him after he was Presbyter, if not after he was advanced to the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, was Grandchild to <hi>Foelix</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> who was Pope, 590. and he is ſaid to have cancell'd his Decree againſt Prieſts Marriages, upon the finding of 600 Infants skulls in a fiſh-pond. Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> II. was Son to Biſhop <hi>Tallerus,</hi> had a Daughter by his Wife <hi>Stephania,</hi> both which were killed after he was Pope, which was, <hi>an.</hi> 863.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> about the year, 900. had children, <hi>viz.</hi> two Sons, and two Daughters.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Armenia,</hi> the Secular Prieſts are all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to marry, elſe they muſt not be admitted to the Prieſthood, <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> permittitur aliquis Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotium aſſumere qui uxorem non duxit.</hi> Berchard. <hi>p.</hi> 95. The Prebendaries of Cathedrals, out of which number they chooſe their Biſhop, are not allowed to marry. In <hi>Biſcay,</hi> they allow not any Prieſt to live in their Villages, except <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he bring his Concubine with him, conceiving it impoſſible for them to keep their wives unto
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45578:56"/>themſeves, if the Curate hath not a woman of his own. <hi>D. H. G. p.</hi> 256. At the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> the Emperor and Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> made inſtance to the Pope, and ſaid it would be of great moment, to grant that Prieſts that are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated becauſe they are married, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and retain their wives, and that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, where there is not a ſufficient number of Prieſts married, men of good life and fame may be admitted to the Prieſthood. <hi>Vid. Hiſtory of the Council of</hi> Trent, p. 813. And we find in the Hiſtory of that Council, that the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Opinion was, the Marriage of Prieſts might be diſpenſed withal. 'Tis true, that this was thought by ſome dangerous, becauſe that marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prieſts would turn their affections and love to their wives and children, and by conſequence to their houſe and Country; ſo that the ſtrict dependance which the Clergy hath on the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick See, would ceaſe; and to grant Marriage to Prieſts, would deſtroy the Eccleſiaſtical Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archy, and make the Pope to be Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> only. <hi>Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>p.</hi> 680. Yea, the famous ſaying of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> II. was then in the mouth of many, <hi>That Prieſts were by the Occidental Church forbid to marry, for good reaſon; but there was ſtronger reaſon to reſtore Marriage to them again.</hi> The two great Reaſons urged at the Council were, Scandal given by incontinent Prieſts; and want of continent perſons fit to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:45578:56"/>exerciſe the Miniſtry, <hi>Hiſt. of C.</hi> Trent, p. 679, &amp; 806. It was in the ſame Council alledged, that the Conſtitution of the Church, forbidding to marry might be taken away by the Pope; or, in caſe the Conſtitution remain ſtill, the Pope may diſpenſe with it: They alledged the examples of thoſe who have been diſpenſed with; and the uſe of Antiquity, that if a Prieſt did marry, the Marriage was good, but the man was ſeparated from the Miniſtry, <hi>C. T. p.</hi> 679. And whereas, as ſome thought; that perſons who were bound to Continency by ſolemn Vow, could not be diſpenſed withal by the Pope; others maintain'd, that the Pope might diſpenſe with theſe alſo, and marvelled at thoſe, who granting the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of ſimple Vows, did deny that of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn, as if it were not moſt clear, that every So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnization is <hi>de Jure poſitivo.</hi> They brought places out of S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> by which it doth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appear, that in his time, ſome Monks did marry; and howſoever it was thought, they offended in it, yet the Marriage was lawful; and St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> reprehendeth thoſe who did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them. And as for Marriage of Prieſts, <hi>Innocent</hi> II. was the firſt, that ordained there ſhould be a nullity in the Marriage. This Pope ſate in the Sea, 1130. <hi>Innocent</hi> III. who bore a heavy hand over our King <hi>John,</hi> and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the Kingdom for ſix years together, was the terrible man againſt Prieſts Marriages:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:45578:57"/>Whereupon we have theſe Verſes by an <hi>Oxford</hi> man.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Priſciana Regula penitus caſſatur,</l>
               <l>Sacerdos per hic &amp; haec olim declinatur</l>
               <l>Nunc per hic ſolum articulatur</l>
               <l>Cum per noſtrum praeſulem hec amo veatur.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>[Prid. Intro. to Hiſtri. 123.]</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Old <hi>Priſcians</hi> Rule henceforth muſt hold no more,</l>
               <l>'Twas <hi>hic &amp; haec Sacerdos</hi> heretofore:</l>
               <l>But now poor <hi>Hic</hi> muſt lie alone perforce,</l>
               <l>For his dear <hi>Haec</hi> our Prelate doth divorce.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> was Pope firſt, <hi>an.</hi> 1198. If we may credit Hiſtory, divers Popes have had their Concubines. <hi>Sixtus</hi> IV. provided for his Concubine <hi>Tireſia</hi> ſhooes covered with Pearl; builded Stews at <hi>Rome,</hi> which brought him 2000 Duckets yearly in-come; he granted the Cardinal <hi>S. Lucia</hi> the uſe of unnatural luſts for three months in the year, <hi>June, July</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. Innocent</hi> the eight a <hi>Genoway,</hi> he had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers baſe children,
<note place="margin">Vid. B. Prid. Hiſt.</note> and gave a great dowry to his Daughter <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorina.</hi> 'Tis ſaid of him,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Octo Nocens pueros genuit totidem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> puellas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hunc merito poteris dicere Roma Patrem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:45578:57"/>
                  <l>Eight Lads, and twice four Girls <hi>Nocens</hi> got,</l>
                  <l>And might not <hi>Rome</hi> him Father term? why not?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth heaped all upon his Baſtards, and carnally uſed his own Daughter <hi>Lucretia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence thoſe Verſes:</p>
            <q>Hic jacet in Tumulo Lucretia nomine ſed re Thais, Alexandri, filia, ſponſa, nurus.</q>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lucrece</hi> by name here li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, but <hi>Thais</hi> in life,</l>
               <l>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Child, Spouſe, and ſons wife.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This Pope entred on the Popedom, an. 1492. <hi>Paul</hi> the third proſtituted his Siſter <hi>Julia For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſia</hi> to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, that he might be made <hi>Cardinal,</hi> committed inceſt with his own Daughter <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> and poyſoned her husband <hi>Boſius Sforſia,</hi> to enjoy her the more freely; he became Pope, 1534. <hi>B. Prid. Hiſt. p.</hi> 145.</p>
            <p>Yet I ſhall grant, 1. That ſingle life is in ſome reſpects to be preferred, as moſt free ordinarily from trouble and care, and in times of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to unfixed perſons, as to their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, affording better opportunity to ſerve God, or to ſuffer for him, and fewer and leſſer tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to deny him. 2. I grant, that thoſe who have made a vow of Celibacy, before or at their entrance into the Miniſtry, or on ſome other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45578:58"/>if they have they have the gift of Continency, are bound to keep it. 3. That 'tis poſſible ſome Votaries of both Sexes, may be free from the groſs vices and crimes charged on moſt of our Votaries, in the days of K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. at the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Abbeys. 4. That in Colledges, for train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up youth in Learning, it is expedient, that thoſe that are Tutors and Readers to youth, be, during ſuch their employment, ſingle. 5. That Presbyters or Prieſts, at times of extraordinary Humiliation, and at times of more ſolemn Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Lord's Supper, ſhall do well to obſerve the old Canons, that forbid the ſociety of their Wives for a time.</p>
            <p>But then I aſſert and avow with the Author to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> chap. 13.4. 1. <hi>That Marriage is honorable among all men,</hi> and therefore among perſons in holy Orders, <hi>and the bed undefiled:</hi> And therefore 2. That the ſociety of a Clergy-man with his wife, whether he was married to her before his Ordination, or after, is lawful; no Adultery, no Uncleanneſs. 3. That for a perſon at his Ordination to make an abſolute vow of ſingle life for all his days, is a raſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Vow. 4. That if a man have made ſuch a Vow, and find he have not, nor cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the gift of Continency, in that caſe he ought to marry. 5. That the Marriage of <hi>Luther</hi> with <hi>Katherine Bora,</hi> on ſuppoſition they could not contain, was lawful. 6. That the Church
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45578:58"/>of <hi>Rome</hi> ſins grievouſly, to <hi>put a yoke upon the neck of the Diſciples of Chriſt,</hi> that officiate in holy things, <hi>which neither we nor our Fathers were able to bear.</hi> 7. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may, and ought to reverſe and repeal her Laws, Canons or Conſtitutions, enjoyning Celibacy on the Clergy; ſo contrary to Scripture, the Apoſtles Canons, the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued practice of the greateſt part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church to this day. 8. That that Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s admitting young Youths and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to make and engage in abſolute ſolemn Vows, that they will live all their days in Celi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacy, is a great ſnare, a grievous ſin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Apoſtles advice concerning young widows, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.14. is oppoſite to the prime bleſſing, <hi>Creſcite &amp; multiplicamini, Increaſe and multiply;</hi> is a great ſcandal to Religion, is a damage to Kingdoms and States, where ſuch are educated idle and uſeleſs to the Publick; is a weakning to their Countrey, a deſtruction of their Race and Family, an occaſion of grievous and horrid luſts and wickedneſſes. 9. That Marriage, notwithſtanding it is lawful to all Ranks, Orders and Degrees of men, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to men in holy Orders, yet it is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. 10. That the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by advancing Matrimony to be a Sacrament, lays claim to the Adminiſtration of it, and to the judging and deciding Matrimonial cauſes, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45578:59"/>ſo brings ſtore of griſt to her Mill. And by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Marriage to Prieſts, doth inrich the Church with that which ſhould otherwiſe be expended on wives and children, and keeps the Clergy in a dependance on <hi>Rome,</hi> having no ſuch near relation as wives and children to withdraw their affections from it. 11. That to aſſert that for a man in holy Orders (ſuppoſe he have made a Vow of Celibacy) to marry, and to accompany with his wife, is worſe than Fornication, yea, than Adultery, is an erroneous and dangerous Poſition; contrary to the holy Scriptures, to ſound Reaſon, to the Ancient Councils and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; <hi>vid. Auſtine de Bono viduitatis:</hi> And if this Book be queſtioned, whether it be his or not, ſee his Epiſtle to one <hi>Bonifacius,</hi> who had vowed a Monaſtical, retired and ſingle life, and yet afterwards did marry; his words are theſe, <hi>Thy wife hindereth me that I cannot exhort thee to this kind of life, without whoſe conſent it is not lawful for thee to contain,</hi> &amp;c. Of this opinion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was <hi>Jerome,</hi> the great Patron of Virginity, <hi>Ep.</hi> 47. <hi>de Suſpecto contubernio vitando.</hi> Of the ſame judgement was <hi>Epiphanius, Haereſ.</hi> 61. who indeed maketh it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> a thing evil, and ſuch as God will judge and puniſh, to forget, neglect, and not perform a Vow made to God; but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> a thing which caſteth men into the condemnation of Hell fire, and plungeth them in everlaſting deſtruction, as to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45578:59"/>live in Adultery. He thinks it better for a man (though he have committed a fault in breaking his Vow, which he may repent of, and be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given) to marry, than by living in continual Adultery, to add one ſin to another, and to plunge himſelf in endleſs deſtruction. And 'tis an abſurd and irrational thing for any man to ſay, that 'tis better to burn, than to marry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe either of his Vow, or of the Command of the Church; for neither a Vow of our own, nor any Command of the Church, can make void the Law of God: if he cannot contain, let him marry, <hi>and to avoid Fornication, let every man have his own wife.</hi> Our Saviour ſaith nothing to the contrary, when he ſaith, <hi>he that can receive it, let him receive it.</hi> We ſpeak only of thoſe who cannot receive it, who cannot contain; and in ſuch caſe, we muſt not make void the Laws of God againſt Adultery and Fornication, in ſeeking to confirm or obſerve the Laws and Conſtitutions of the Church. In this caſe, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be better to obey God or man, judge ye.</hi> I ſhall not here go about to ſhew, that the Anſwers of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others, to the Authorities that are brought on our ſide, are but fig-leaves to cover the nakedneſs of their cauſe, and eaſily blown away; but I ſhall direct my Reader to Bp. <hi>Jewel</hi> his Defence of his Apology, Dr. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church, <hi>B.</hi> 5. <hi>ch.</hi> 57. to Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi>'s Anſwer to the <hi>Rhemiſt's Teſtam.</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:45578:60"/>on <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. and on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. to <hi>Calixtus de Conjugio Clericorum,</hi> to Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>'s Honour of the married Clergy. Nor ſhall I go about to anſwer the particular ſayings of ſome Fathers to the diſparagement of Marriage. It ſufficeth, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the Ancient Church on her ſide; the deſires of many Learned, Worthy men that have been in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> the practice of the greateſt number of Chriſtian Churches in the world at this day; ſo far as to juſtifie the lawfulneſs of married men, to be admitted to holy Orders, and to officiate in and about holy things, notwithſtanding their having wives; and that the bleſſing of God is, and hath been upon our married Clergy, no other Nation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling them in Learning, Piety, or the gift of Preaching; that ſaying ſtill holding good, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Marriage, <hi>Stupor mundi Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Britannicus.</hi> If it be objected, That this Marriage doth ſpoil our Charity and Hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and proves a temptation to Covetouſneſs. I anſwer, That <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 4.7, 8. ſays, <hi>There is a vanity and diſſatisfaction, and unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in heaping up riches, even by ſingle perſons.</hi> And 'tis obſerved by a ſober and learned Caſuiſt of our own [Mr. <hi>Capel</hi>] <hi>That ſingle perſons, and thoſe that have but few children, oft-times prove more covetous, than thoſe that are married, and have many children;</hi> alledging, <hi>that the latter are by
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:45578:60"/>daily and frequent experiences and layings out, habituated to part with money, and ſo a peny comes not (as from ſome others, like a drop of blood from their hearts.</hi> I ſay further, that great things have been done by the married Clergy, and other married perſons in our days, if it were neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we might inſtance in particulars. It hath been ſaid, <hi>That</hi> Pater Noſter <hi>built Churches, and</hi> Our Father <hi>pull'd them down;</hi> but it hath been proved and publiſhed to the world, that as many and great Acts of Piety and Charity have been done in <hi>England</hi> ſince the Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as in the like number of years in times of Popery. And whatever is or may be ſaid or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the contrary, as if the allowing of the marriage of the Clergy was an impoveriſhment of the Church and Country, and a damage to the Kingdom; I dare ſay, they that would remove the married Clergy, to bring in the Monks, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to recompence the Churches, their Countrys, and the Kings and Kingdoms damage. Who can more earneſtly pray for, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the weal of their own King and Country, than thoſe who have ſuch great bonds and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts to deſire and endeavour it? And who is like to be moſt at home amongſt his own people, if not he that hath amongſt them continually a wife, the deſire of his eyes, and children, which he loves as his own eyes?</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
